<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"-->
<chapter>
  <title>XOCL</title>

  <para></para>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The basic technology that underpins XMF-Mosaic is a programming
    language called XOCL. The programming language is very similar to standard
    object-oriented languages such as Java or C#. In addition, XOCL is a
    meta-programming language meaning that it provides facilities for
    inspecting and controlling its own behaviour. This is the key to
    supporting flexible tool development. Tools defined in XOCL can inspect
    and interpret other tools defined in XOCL. Tools defined in XOCL can
    generate other tools defined in XOCL, and can generate tools defined in
    other languages such as Java.</para>

    <para>This document is a technical description of XOCL. It defines all
    aspects of the language and provides a complete definition of the
    programming constructs and what they do. This document is not a
    description of how to use XOCL. For that you should read the example
    Walkthroughs in the Bluebook.</para>

    <para>The document is structured as follows: the basic architecture of
    XOCL is describes in terms of what it does and how programs are
    represented at the lowest level; the basic data types provided by XOCL are
    defined; XOCL program structure is defined including conditional
    constructs, binding constructs, errors and looping. Finally, the interface
    of each basic data type is defined.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Purpose</title>

      <para>XOCL is a programming language that is intended to support
      powerful programming over meta-data. In achieving this aim, the
      following objectives have been addressed:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Efficiency</emphasis>. XOCL provides a programming
          language that is used on primarily data intensive applications (as
          opposed to real-time applications, safety critical applications or
          applications that require intensive numeric processing). XOCL will
          process large data sets (several tens of thousands of objects) using
          average memory and average processor resources.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Extensibility</emphasis>. XOCL is designed to be
          highly extensible. New language features can be added to XOCL by
          defining an XBNF grammar for the new feature and the rule to process
          the new syntax structures. In many cases, new syntax structures can
          be translated to basic XOCL; this provides a powerful macro-facility
          for defining declarative language constructs.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Dynamic</emphasis>. XOCL is designed to be highly
          configurable and easy to modify at run-time. Although XOCL is a
          compiled language, new definitions can be introduced at any time
          during execution and existing definitions can be modified at
          run-time.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Meta-circularity</emphasis>. XOCL is designed to
          allow existing language features to be extended and modified. XOCL
          understands its own rules of execution. New tools can introduce
          modification to these rules. XOCL can process its own syntax; the
          XOCL compiler and interpreter is written in XOCL.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Standards</emphasis>. XMF-Mosaic aims to make
          standards available wherever these are appropriate. The environment
          provides a MOF-like meta-modelling language and a UML-like modeling
          language. The XML facilities of XMF can be used to import and export
          XMI encoded data. The language XOCL is based on the UML Object
          Constraint Language.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Conventional</emphasis>. XOCL aims to provide a
          language that is as familiar to users as possible whilst achieving
          the aim of being a powerful basis for tool generation. The basic
          language features of XOCL will be familiar to users of standard
          object-oriented programming languages such as Java.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Complete</emphasis>. XOCL provides a complete
          solution to tool construction. XOCL is not a scripting language
          (i.e. a lightweight language used as glue for programs written in
          other languages). XOCL provides features that support the
          implementation of industrial strength tools, including sophisticated
          data structures, error handling and a variety of input/output
          mechanisms.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Language Basics</title>

      <para>XOCL programs consist of a collection of units (text files). Each
      unit can be compiled and loaded separately; however, there are
      restrictions on the order of compilation and loading multiple units that
      must be followed; these are explained in this section. A unit is
      processed by loading and then evaluating it. Loading involves syntax
      analysis.</para>

      <para>A unit has entries in the following order:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Parser declarations. A parser declaration is processed by the
          syntax analysis phase. Typically a declaration imports a collection
          of grammars that define new language constructs. Each language
          construct in the rest of the unit must be declared before it is
          used. Basic XOCL is imported by default.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>NameSpace imports. Global variables must be imported before
          they can be used. Each global variable is defined in a name space.
          Importing the name space makes all the names it defines available in
          the rest of the unit. The names in Root and XCore are imported by
          default.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Commands and definitions. The rest of the unit is a sequence
          of any valid XOCL syntax as defined in terms of the parser
          declarations and imports that precede it. Definitions take the form
          of the keyword context followed by a name and then an expression
          whose value is a named element. The name must reference a name
          space. The effect of a definition is to add the named element to the
          named name space. Commands take the form of XOCL syntax followed by
          a semi-colon (;).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A typical unit has the form shown on the right. All components
          are optional but, if present, must occur in the order shown.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><programlisting>// Comments at the head of the file….

parserImport &lt;PATH&gt;;
// More parser imports…

// Comments here….

import &lt;PATH&gt;;
// More imports….

// Comments here….

context &lt;PATH&gt;
  &lt;NAMEDELEMENT&gt;

// More defs….

&lt;COMMAND&gt;
// More commands….</programlisting></para>

      <para>When a unit is loaded, its syntax is analysed with respect to the
      parser declarations. If the syntax is legal then the unit is evaluated.
      Evaluation processes each name space import in turn. Each import is
      performed in the context of all preceding imports. If the imports are
      successful then the rest of the unit is evaluated in the context of the
      imported names. Definitions are evaluated by constructing the named
      element, referencing the name space and adding the named element to the
      name space. Commands are evaluated; any result produced by the commands
      is discarded.</para>

      <para>The effect of evaluating a unit is the result of adding all
      definitions to their name spaces and any side-effects produced by the
      commands.</para>

      <para>Note that although the basic unit of execution is the text file,
      XOCL is a meta-language and can be used to process definitions and
      expressions at run-time. This makes XOCL ideal for handling expressions
      typed at a command interpreter and definitions typed in forms as part of
      a user interface.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Overview of Syntax</title>

      <para>XOCL is a textual language. When a unit is loaded its syntax is
      processed prior to evaluation. The first stage of syntax analysis if to
      recognize lexical tokens. A lexical token is a sequence of characters
      read from the input starting with a non-whitespace character. This
      section provides an overview of the token types:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Integer tokens start with a numeric character and continue up
          to, but not including, the first non-numeric character.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Parentheses ( and ).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Braces { and }.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Dot .</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>At @.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Comma ,.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Special tokens are those that do not consist of an
          alpha-numeric character and are not listed elsewhere. Examples of
          special tokens are infix operators such as * and +, arrow -&gt; and
          quasi-quotes [| and |].</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Name tokens start with an alpha-character and continue up to,
          but not including, the first non-alpha-numeric character.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Symbol tokens start with a ‘ and end with the following
          ‘.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>String tokens start with a “ and end with the following “.
          Within strings the following escape characters are useful:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Newline \n</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Tab \t</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Return \r</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>String quote \”</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Basic Data Types</title>

    <para>XOCL is an object-oriented language that runs on the Virtual
    Machine (XVM) and uses a library of class definitions (written in XOCL)
    called XCore. Most data types in XMF are represented as instances of XCore
    classes; however, there is a sub-set of XCore, that is fundamental to XOCL
    and its execution on XVM. These classes are the basic data types necessary
    to run XOCL. They are listed here. Their interface definitions are given
    in subsequent sections of this document.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Booleans. A boolean value is either true or false. Booleans are
        used to control branches in execution.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Clients. XMF-Mosaic can act as a client that connects to and
        communicates with an external server. The connection is constructed
        and maintained through a client value.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Channels. XOCL performs input and output through channels.
        StandardInputChannel and StandardOutputChannel define interfaces that
        are implemented by a wide variety of concrete classes that support
        different forms of input and output; for example: file i/o.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Daemons. A daemon is a value that can be attached to an object
        in XOCL that monitors the state of the object. A daemon is activated
        when the object changes state.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Integers. Positive and negative integers in the range -24^2 to
        +24^2.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Floats. 64 bit floating point numbers.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Null. The undefined value.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Objects. An object is a data value with slots. Each slot has a
        name and a value. All data in XMF is represented in on the formats in
        this list. Most data in XMF is represented as objects. All types
        (classes) in XMF are objects and all types have their own
        types.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Operations. An operation has a name, arguments and a body. The
        body of the operation is XOCL program code. When the operation is
        invoked, it is supplied with values for the arguments and it performs
        its body. An operation invocation returns the value produced by the
        body. Operations are the basis for all execution in XOCL. Operations
        are proper values in the seinse that they can be passed as argument
        values and stored in slots.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Sequences. XOCL provides lisp-like lists which it calls
        sequences. A sequence is either a cons pair with a head and a tail or
        is the empty sequence. Cons pairs have state such that the head and
        the tail may be updated. Sequences provide a very flexible and
        efficient way of organising collections of data that change over
        time.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Sets. XOCL provides a data type for representing sets. A set is
        like a sequence except that it has no state, its elements are
        unordered and it cannot contain duplicates. Although sets can be
        defined in terms of objects and sequences, they are provided as a
        basic data type for efficiency reasons (on the rare occasions that
        very large sets are necessary).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Strings. A string is a sequence of character codes. Two strings
        are equal when they have the same sequence of character codes. A
        string has no state.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Symbols. A symbol is a string with state. Two symbols are equal
        when they are the same data value in computer memory. Symbols are very
        similar to strings except they facilitate efficient name lookup in
        dictionaries. Named elements in XCore use symbols.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Tables. A table associates keys with values. Keys have hash
        codes that make lookup and update efficient in tables.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Threads. XOCL is multi-threaded. Each thread is a separate unit
        of computation that can share global data with other threads. XOCL
        multi-threading is provided to allow XMF to monitor interactions with
        multiple clients (although could be used for a variety of tasks). It
        is not expected that there would be more than 10 – 20 threads active
        at any given time.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Vectors. Vectors are fixed size, indexable sequences of
        values.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Program Constructs</title>

    <para>As described above, XOCL programs consist of units. Each unit
    contains parser declarations followed by name space imports and then a
    sequence of commands and definitions. Both commands and definitions
    contain general XOCL expressions; an expression is the basic component of
    an XOCL language construct. All XOCL language features are evaluated to
    produce a value; in addition some features produce a side effect as a
    result of evaluation. Expressions fall into a small number of different
    categories depending on how they are evaluated. This section provides an
    overview of XOCL program features and their evaluation mechanisms.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Self Evaluating Expressions</title>

      <para>The simplest type of XOCL expression is self evaluating, these are
      often referred to as constants and include integer, string, Boolean and
      float literals. In addition, the empty sequence Seq{} and the empty set
      Set{} are self evaluating.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Variables and Update</title>

      <para>A name is an XOCL expression that evaluates to a value depending
      on the association that the name has in the current context. In general,
      names refer to variable locations that contain values and are often
      referred to as variables. XOCL supports three types of variable: local,
      global and slot. Examples of local variables are operation parameters
      and let-introduced names. Examples of global variables are names that
      have been imported from name spaces. Slot variables refer to the state
      of the currently executing object.</para>

      <para>Slot variables may be qualified or unqualified. A qualified
      reference includes the object that contains the slot followed by dot (.)
      and the name of the slot. An unqualified reference is just the name of
      the slot: such a reference assumes the object containing the slot to be
      self.</para>

      <para>Global variable references occur may be qualified or unqualified.
      A qualified reference references the global variable via some or all of
      its containing name spaces; this is similar to a path in a file system.
      For example P::Q::V refers to the variable V in the name space Q which
      itself is contained in the name space P. The name space P is assumed to
      be available at the point of reference because it is imported. An
      unqualified reference to a global variable does not include any
      containing name spaces: they must be imported at the point of
      reference.</para>

      <para>Variables may be updated using the := operator. The left hand
      operand must be a variable and the right hand operator must be an
      expression. The expression is evaluated and the resulting value is
      placed in the variable location. Slot updates must use qualified slot
      variables. Global updates must use qualified global variables.</para>

      <para>The following class definition contains examples of all types of
      variable reference and update:</para>

      <para><programlisting>context P
  @Class C extends D, Q::E
    @Attribute v : Element end
    @Operation getV():Element
      v
    end
    @Operation setV(newV:Element)
      P::lastGoodV := self.v;
      self.v := newV
    end
    @Operation lastGoodV():Element
      import P
      in lastGoodV
      end
    end
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>Line 1 is an unqualified global reference to the name space P.
      Line 2 contains an unqualified global reference to D and a qualified
      global reference to E. Line 5 is an unqualified slot reference to v.
      Line 8 contains a qualified global update for lastGoodV and a qualified
      slot reference to v. Line 9 contains a qualified slot update for v and a
      local reference to newV. Line 13 contains an unqualified global
      reference to P and line 14 contains an unqualified global reference
      (since it has been imported) to lastGoodV.</para>

      <para>Local variables are typically created when values are supplied as
      arguments to an operation or when local definitions are executed. The
      association between the Local variable name and the value persist for
      the duration of the operation definition or the execution of the body of
      the local block. In both cases, as the name suggests, variable values
      can change by side effect.</para>

      <para>Local variables are established when arguments are passed to an
      operation or using a let expression. In both cases the variable can be
      referenced in the body of the expression, but not outside the body. In
      both cases the variables can be updated using v := e. Suppose we require
      an operation that takes two integers and returns a pair where the head
      is the smallest integer and the tail is the other integer:</para>

      <para><programlisting>context Root
  @Operation orderedPair(x,y)
    let min = 0;
        max = 0
    in if x &lt; y then min := x else min := y end;
       if x &gt; y then max := x else max := y end;
       Seq{min | max}
    end
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>The definition of orderedPair shows how a let expression can
      introduce a number of variables (in this case min and max). If the let -
      bindings are separated using ; then the bindings are established
      in-parallel meaning that the variables cannot affect each other (i.e.
      the value for max cannot refer to min and vice versa). If the bindings
      are separated using then they are established in-series meaning that
      values in subsequent bindings can refer to variables in earlier
      bindings, for example:</para>

      <para><programlisting>context Root
  @Operation orderedPair(x,y)
    let min = if x &lt; y then x else y end then
        max = if min = x then y else x end
    in Seq{min | max}
    end
  end</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Calling Operations</title>

      <para>An operation is invoked by directly invoking it on some argument
      values or by sending an object a message for which the operation has
      been defined as the handler. The two types of invocation use the same
      underlying evaluation machinery, but are syntactically very different.
      In both cases there is only one parameter passing mechanism: values are
      passed into the operation and values with state can be modified by the
      operation. Variables cannot be modified in the sense of Pascal or Ada
      out parameters. The parameter passing mechanism is directly equivalent
      to that of Java.</para>

      <para>Operations are applied to arguments using the conventional
      procedure call notation:</para>

      <para><programlisting>p(arg1,arg2,…,argn)</programlisting></para>

      <para>where p is an XOCL expression that evaluates to an operator and
      each argi is an XOCL expression that evaluates to produce an argument
      value.</para>

      <para>Messages are sent to a value using the conventional method
      invocation notation:</para>

      <para><programlisting>o.m(arg1,arg2,…,argn)</programlisting></para>

      <para>where o is an XOCL expression that evaluates to produce a value
      (the receiver), m is a name and argi are the operation parameter
      expressions. To calculate the operation that is invoked, XOCL finds the
      type of o, and calculates its operator precedence list (OPL). The OPL
      contains all the operators defined by the type of o with the name m in
      order of most recently defined (with respect to inheritance) first. The
      first operation in the OPL is invoked.</para>

      <para>The receiver of a message defines the value of self in the body of
      the operation invocation. In the case of direct operator application,
      the value of self is that which was in scope when the operator was
      defined. The value of self can be changed by sending the operation an
      invoke message:</para>

      <para><programlisting>p.invoke(o,Seq{arg1,arg2,…,argn})</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Infix Operators</title>

      <para>XOCL supports infix notation for the usual arithmetic and boolean
      operators. In most cases the evaluation of an infix expression will
      evaluate both sub-expressions in left to right order and then perform
      the appropriate function on the results. The exceptions are:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>p andthen q evaluates p, if p is false then q is not
            evaluated, otherwise this behaves as p and q.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>p orelse q evaluates p, if p is true then q is not evaluated
            otherwise this behaves as p or q.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Prefix Operators</title>

      <para>XOCL supports one prefix operator – not. Note that prefix – for
      negative numbers is not supported (use infix – as in: 0-n).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sequencing</title>

      <para>XOCL expressions may produce side effects, either by changing the
      state of values, producing output or consuming input. Expression
      evaluation is controlled using the semi-colon (;) operator that
      sequences evaluation: e1; e2 is evaluated by evaluating e1 and then
      evaluating e2. The result of the sequenced expression is the value of
      e2. This operator associates to the right.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Special Forms</title>

      <para>An XOCL special form is an expression that has its own evaluation
      rules that do not necessarily follow the usual rules of sub-expression
      evaluation followed by operator call. This section lists the special
      forms and defines their evaluation rules.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Conditional expressions are defined using standard
          if…then…else…end notation. The test following the if is evaluated,
          if it is true then the consequent expression is evaluated otherwise
          the alternative expression is evaluated.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A definition occurs in a program unit as the keyword context
          followed by a name space and a n expression whose value is a named
          element. The definition causes the named element to be added to
          thename space when it is performed. The only place this type of
          definition can occur is at the top level of an evaluation
          unit.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Local variables are introduced using a let expression: let
          bindings in body end. The bindings introduce local variable names
          and their initial values. The body is an XOCL expression whose
          evaluation may reference the local variables. The variables are
          discarded when the evaluation is complete and the value of the let
          expression is the value of its body.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A set or sequence is constructed using the form
          Set{exp1,exp2,…,expn} and Seq{exp1,exp2,…,expn}. The sub-expressions
          are evaluated and the result is a set or sequence containing the
          values.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>XOCL is based on OCL which provides a number of convenient
          types of iteration expression. These have the form: s-&gt;iterOp(v |
          body) where s is an expression whose value is a set or sequence,
          iterOp is one of forAll, exists, select, collect or reject, v is a
          variable name and body is an expression. Depending on the iteration
          operation the body expression is evaluated in a context where v is
          bound to successive elements selected from s. A special form of
          iteration expression is also provided: s-&gt;iterate(v w = e | body)
          where w is initialized to e and body is evaluated with v bound to
          successive elements of s; at each evaluation w is rebound to the
          value produced by body.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>OCL provides a notation for invoking sequence and set
          operations: s-&gt;collOp and s-&gt;collOp(arg1,arg2,…,argn). These
          are retained in XOCL for compatibility with OCL, but are unnecessary
          since method calling notation works just as well.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A name space is imported for the scope of an expression e by
          import n in e end. All of the names defined in n are available in
          the expression e.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>XOCL provides an exception mechanism for handling errors and
          other exceptional circumstances during execution. An exception is
          created and thrown from the point of error using a throw e command
          (an example of an XOCL construct that does not behave like a
          standard expression). The expression e is evaluated and can produce
          any value. XCore provides a collection of exception classes that can
          be used and extended. The exception is caught by the most recently
          established try … catch(x) … end expression. The exception can be
          handled in by the catch or may be re-thrown to the next try
          expression.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Quasi-Quotes</title>

      <para>XOCL is a language that provides features for meta-programming. A
      key feature of meta-programming is language processing: the ability to
      construct, transform and manipulate programs. XOCL provides quasi-quotes
      [| and |] for this purpose. Quasi-quotes can be placed around any XOCL
      expression e (including XOCL language extensions), the value of the
      resulting expression [| e |] is the syntax structure for e (as opposed
      to the value of e). For example: the value of [| x + 1 |] is not an
      integer, but a syntax structure representing an addition expression
      whose operator is + and whose left operand is a variable with name x and
      whose right operand is the constant 1.</para>

      <para>Within quasi-quotes any expression surrounded by drop braces &lt;
      and &gt; is expected to produce syntax that is inserted into the syntax
      structure constructed by the quotes. For example:</para>

      <para><programlisting>let e = [| x + 1 |]
in [| y * &lt;x&gt; |]
end</programlisting></para>

      <para>line 1 creates a syntax structure called e that is then inserted
      into the syntax structure as the right operand of the multiplication
      expression in line 2. The resulting structure is equivalent
      to:<programlisting>[| y * (x + 1) |]</programlisting></para>

      <para>Quasi quotes and drop braces are very important when
      meta-programming with languages. They make constructing code templates
      very easy. Code templates are used to construct XOCL language extensions
      and to facilitate mappings that translate from one language to
      another.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Meta Character @</title>

      <para>XOCL is an extensible language. New language features are easy to
      add to XOCL to provide new expression types, new command and new
      declarative definitions. A big problem of current programming languages
      is that they cannot be extended very easily. Thus, it is not possible to
      construct abstraction mechanisms that capture the key features of the
      application domain. This results in large amounts of program code that
      is difficult to maintain. Examples of such patterns are: new types of
      looping construct; a state machine definition; the observer pattern; new
      types of interface definition; coding standards; specific types of
      classes such as containers.</para>

      <para>XOCL provides a novel feature that allows new language constructs
      to be conveniently added to the language. Once they are added, the new
      features are seamlessly integrated with all other language constructs.
      The language feature that supports this is the meta-character @.</para>

      <para>When an XOCL unit is processed it is syntactically analysed and
      then evaluated. During the syntax analysis phase, if an expression
      starts with the character @ then the analyzer is informed that the
      characters up to and including the corresponding end are to be processed
      by a language extension. A language extension is defined by providing a
      grammar that parses the characters from the @ to the end; the grammar is
      expected to synthesize and return a syntax construct. Grammars can be
      attached to classes and the name following the @ should be a class that
      defines a grammar. A syntax construct is required to implement the
      Performable interface that allows the second phase of XOCL unit
      processing. These two features: grammars and Performable are all that is
      necessary to allow XOCL to be arbitrarily extended with new
      constructs.</para>

      <para>Typically, syntax classes implement the Performable interface by
      translating to existing XOCL syntax classes (that already implement the
      Performable interface). This form of language extension is termed sugar
      and the processif translation is called desugaring.</para>

      <para>XOCL makes extensive use of the @ feature. Looping constructs such
      as While, Find and For are all implemented as extensions of the basic
      XOCL language. Definitions for classes, packages, constraints and
      operations are defined using @.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Documentation</title>

    <para>Comments can be inserted into XOCL in two ways. The first way is
    using the standard // &lt;line of text&gt; line comment and /*
    &lt;para&gt; */ paragraph comments. These can only be used in text files
    and are ignored by the parser.</para>

    <para>The second way is using the @Doc &lt;some text&gt; end syntax. The
    text within an @Doc is ignored for the purposes of executing the
    statement. However, the comment is parsed and is stored as part of the
    XOCL statement. This means that documentation attached to an XOCL
    expression can be processed as part of a model. Note a semicolon is not
    required if the documentation is placed at the head of the code body
    (otherwise it is). Here is an example of its use:</para>

    <para><programlisting>context Float
  @Operation max(other:Integer):Integer
    @Doc
      Compares a float with other and returns
      the maximum value.
    end
    if self &gt; other
    then self
    else other
    end
  end</programlisting></para>

    <para>Note, there are currently some limitations to the characters that
    can be used in an @Doc expression. In particular, the string end must not
    occur in a @Doc body, even if it is embedded in a word. To resolve this, a
    separator can be used, e.g. send becomes sen-d.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Error Handling</title>

    <para>When an error occurs in XOCL, the source of the error throws an
    exception. The exception is a value that, in general, contains a
    description of the problem and any data that might help explain the reason
    why the problem occurred. An exception is thrown to the most recently
    established handler; intermediate code is discarded. If no handler exists
    then the XMF VM will terminate. In most cases, the exception is caught by
    a user-defined handler or, for example in the case of the XMF console, a
    handler established by the command interpreter.</para>

    <para>When an exception is caught, the handler can inspect the contents of
    the exception and decide what to do. For example it may be necessary to
    re-throw the exception to the next-most recently established handler,
    since it cannot be dealt with. On the other hand, it is usual to catch the
    exception, print a message, patch up the problem, or just give up on the
    requested action.</para>

    <para>Exception handling is performed by a try catch expression with the
    following form:<programlisting>try
  normal
catch(x)
  abnormal
end</programlisting>The try expression evaluates the normal sub-expression
    that may perform an arbitrary amount of computation. If the normal
    expression completes without throwing an exception then its value is
    returned as the value of the try expression. Alternatively, an exception
    is thrown at some point during the execution of normal:</para>

    <para><programlisting>throw e</programlisting></para>

    <para>where e is an expression that produces the exception. An exception
    can be any value, but is typically an instance of the class Exception or
    one of its sub-classes. An exception is handled by the most recently
    established try expression. The evaluation of normal is terminated and
    execution passes to line 3. The variable x is bound to the thrown
    exception and abnormal is evaluated. If abnormal evaluates without
    throwing an exception then the value of abnormal is the value returned by
    the try expression. Otherwise, abnormal throws an exception (perhaps x)
    that is handled by the next most recently established try
    expression.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Control Statements</title>

    <para>Flow of control in XOCL is controlled by the constructs defined in
    this section. All the basic control statements are supported, including
    If, Case, While and For. In addition, XOCL supports convenient notations
    for iterating over collections.</para>

    <section>
      <title>If</title>

      <para>An if expression if used to choose between alternative expressions
      based on the outcome of a boolean expression. The different forms of if
      expression are outlined as follows:</para>

      <programlisting>1  if test
2  then consequent
3  end
4 
5  if test 
6  then consequent
7  else alternative
8  end
9 
10 if test1
11 then consequent1
12 elseif test2
13 then consequent2
14 elseif test3
15 then …
16 else alternative
17 end</programlisting>

      <para>Lines 1-3 show that an if can be used to construct a guarded
      expression. If the test in line 1 produces true then the consequent in
      line 2 is evaluated and produces the value fo the if expression
      otherwise nothing is evaluated and the value of the if expression is
      undefined.</para>

      <para>Lines 5 – 8 show how a n if expression is used to choose between
      two different expressions. If the expression at line 5 produces true
      then the expression at line 6 is evaluated and produces the value of the
      if expression. Otherwise the expression at line 7 is evaluated and
      produces the value of the if expression.</para>

      <para>Lines 10 – 17 show how the elseif keyword can be used to avoid
      deeply nested if expressions.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Case</title>

      <para>A case expression is used to dispatch on a sequence of values. The
      simplest form of a case expression is shown as follows:</para>

      <programlisting>@Case e of
  p1 do 
    e1 
  end
  p2 do
    e2
  end
  …
  pn do
    en
  end
  else x
end</programlisting>

      <para>The case expression is evaluated as follows. The expression e at
      line 1 is evaluated to produce a value v. If v matches pattern p1 then
      e1 is evaluated and produces the value of the case expression. Otherwise
      if value v matches p2 then e2 is evaluated and produces the value of the
      case expression. Matching continues sequentially until a pattern pi
      matches and the corresponding expression ei produces the value of the
      case or the else-clause is reached. If the else-clause is reached then x
      is evaluated and produces the value of the case expression. Note that
      the else-clause is optional.</para>

      <para>Note that the semantics of pattern matching is covered elsewhere
      in this document. The simplest form of pattern matching is against basic
      values:</para>

      <programlisting>@Case x of
  1 do 
    // The value of x is 1…
  end
  2 do
    // The value of x is 2…
  end
  …
  100 do
   // The value of x is 100…
  end
  else self.error(“Illegal value for x: “ + x.toString())
end</programlisting>

      <para>In general a case statement can match over a sequence of
      values:</para>

      <programlisting>@Case e1,e2,…,en of
  p11,p12,…,p1n do 
    b1 
  end
  p21,p22,…,p2n do
    b2
  end
  …
  pm1,pm2,…,pmn do
    bm
  end
  else x
end</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>CaseInt</title>

      <para>An integer case expression dispatches on the value of an integer.
      An integer case expression is much more efficient that a case expression
      because it compiles to a simple indexed dispatch in XVM. The following
      is an example that returns true when the value of char is an
      alpha-numeric character code:</para>

      <programlisting>       @CaseInt[256] char of
         " "-&gt;at(0) do false end
         "\n"-&gt;at(0) do false end
         "\t"-&gt;at(0) do false end
         "\r"-&gt;at(0) do false end
         "("-&gt;at(0) do false end
         ")"-&gt;at(0) do false end
         "\""-&gt;at(0) do false end
         "0"-&gt;at(0) to "9"-&gt;at(0) do true end
         "A"-&gt;at(0) to "z"-&gt;at(0) do true end
         else false
     end</programlisting>

      <para>Line 1 states that the range of values for char is 0 to 255. Each
      case arm uses s-&gt;at(0) to include a literal character code. Note that
      the values in case arms may be any XOCL expression but that the
      expression must have a value at compile time. A case arm has values to
      be matched before the keyword do. The values can take the following
      forms:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A constant integer valued expression.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A range x to y where x and y are constant integer valued
          expressions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A sequence of integer case values separated with comma
          (,).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>TypeCase</title>

      <para>In a pure OO program it should not be necessary to test the type
      of a value, all computation should be performed using message passing.
      However, few if any applications are pure and testing the type of a
      value at run-time is occasionally necessary. All values in XOCL can
      respond to an isKindOf message whose single argument is an XCore
      classifier. The return is a Boolean value determining whether or not the
      value is considered, with respect to inheritance, to be an instance of
      the classifier. Where there are many such tests on a value it is more
      declarative and potentially more efficient to use the TypeCase special
      form:<programlisting>@TypeCase(x)
     type1 do
        exp1
     end
     type2 do
       exp2
     end
     ….
     typen do
        expn
     end
     else d
  end
</programlisting>The expression x is evaluated in line 1 to produce a value.
      Each type (lines 2,5 etc) is a name or path referencing a classifier. If
      the value of x is of type type1 then exp1 is evaluated and produces the
      value of the case expression. Otherwise, checking proceeds case by case
      until the optional default case us evaluated. A value v is of type t
      when it is a direct instance of t or when the direct type of v inherits
      from t.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>While</title>

      <para>A While loop performs an action until a condition is satisfied
      (note a named element may use a symbol for its name so we ensure the
      name is a string using the toString operation):</para>

      <programlisting>context Root
  @Operation findElement(N:Set(NamedElement),name:String)
    let found = null
    in @While not N-&gt;isEmpty do
         let n = N-&gt;sel
         in if n.name().toString() = name
            then found := n
            else N := N-&gt;excluding(n)
            end
         end
       end;
       found
    end
  end</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>For</title>

      <para>It is often the case that While loops are used to iterate through
      a collection. This pattern is captured by a For loop:</para>

      <programlisting>context Root
  @Operation findElement(N:Set(NamedElement),name:String)
    let found = null
    in @For n in N do
         if n.name().toString() = name
         then found := n
         end
       end;
       found
    end
  end</programlisting>

      <para>In general a For loop @For x in S do e end is equivalent to the
      following While loop:</para>

      <programlisting>let forColl = S;
    isFirst = true
in @While not forColl-&gt;isEmpty do
     let x = forColl-&gt;sel
     in forColl := forColl-&gt;excluding(x);
        let isLast = forColl-&gt;isEmpty
        in e;
           isFirst := false
        end
     end
   end
end</programlisting>

      <para>Where the variables forColl, isFirst and isLast are scoped over
      the body of the loop e. These can be useful if we want the body action
      to depend on whether this is the first or last iteration, for example
      turning a sequence into a string:</para>

      <programlisting>context Seq(Operation)
  @Operation toString()
    let s = "Seq{"
    in @For e in self do
         s := s + e.toString();
         if not isLast then s := s + "," end
       end;
       s + "}"
    end
  end</programlisting>

      <para>A For loop may return a result. The keyword do states that the
      body of the For loop is an action and that the result of performing the
      entire loop will be ignored when the loop exits. Alternatively, the
      keyword produce states that the loop will return a sequence of values.
      The values are the results returned by the loop body each time it is
      performed. For example, suppose we want to calculate the sequence of
      names from a sequence of people:</para>

      <programlisting>context Root
  @Operation getNames(people:Seq(Person)):Seq(String)
    @For person in people produce 
      person.name 
    end
  end</programlisting>

      <para>The keyword in is a For-loop directive. After in the loop expects
      one or more collections. The in directive supports multiple variables.
      This feature is useful when stepping through multiple collections in
      sync, as in:</para>

      <programlisting>context Root
  @Operation createTable(names:Seq(String),addresses:Seq(String),telNos:Seq(String))
    @For name,address,telNo in names,addresses,telNos produce
      Seq{name,address,telNo}
    end
  end
</programlisting>

      <para>A For-loop also has a where option. This allows the elements to be
      filtered. The following only iterates over names of persons that are not
      excluded.</para>

      <programlisting>context Root
  @Operation getNames(people:Seq(Person),excluded:Seq(Person)):Seq(String)
    @For person in people where not excluded-&gt;includes(person) do
      person.name 
    end
  end</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Find</title>

      <para>The Find construct is used to perform an action in terms of an
      element of a collection. Typically we want to find the first element in
      a collection that satisfies a given predicate and to perform an action.
      If no value exists that satisfies the predicate then we optionally want
      to perform some other action. This construct captures that
      pattern.</para>

      <para>As an example, imagine we want find a transition in a statemachine
      whose targetName is equal to the name of a state, and that when we do,
      we want to return the State object with that name, or if one does not
      exist, return the initial state. The following operation getTarget()
      implements this using Find.</para>

      <programlisting>@Operation getTarget(name: String):XCore::Element
      let next = null
      in @Find(t,transition)
           when t.targetName = name
           do next := states-&gt;select(s |
                       s.name = name)-&gt;sel
           else next := states-&gt;select(s |
                       s.name = startName)-&gt;sel
         end;
         next
      end
    end</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Iterators</title>

      <para>There are number of important collection operations that can be
      used to iterate over elements in a collection to produce a result. Each
      iterator operation has an iterator variable, which is matched with each
      element of the collection in turn. An iterator expression is then
      evaluated against the variable to produce a result.</para>

      <para>There are four main iterator operations: select, collect, reject
      and iterate.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Select</title>

        <para><programlisting>C-&gt;select(c | &lt;expression with c&gt;)</programlisting>Select
        filters the elements in the collection. The element c is added to the
        result if and only if the &lt;Expr&gt; is true. The following example
        will return only those values of the set that are greater than
        5:<programlisting>Set{1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10}-&gt;select(i | i &gt; 5)</programlisting>In
        the context of a class model, select statements are very useful for
        filtering collections of objects subject to some property. For
        instance, this operation returns all states of a StateMachine that
        match the name x and which are not an initial state of the
        StateMachine (see Part 2 of this Reference Manual):<programlisting>context StateMachine
@Operation statesForName(x):Set(Element)
  states-&gt;select(s | s.name = x and not startName = x)
end</programlisting></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Reject</title>

        <para><programlisting>C-&gt;reject(c | &lt;expression with c&gt;)</programlisting>Reject
        is the converse of select. It rejects any elements where &lt;Expr&gt;
        returns true.</para>

        <para>As an example, the following rejects all the values of the
        sequence of characters that are alphabetically greater than the
        character "a":<programlisting>Seq{"a","b"}-&gt;reject(x | x &gt; "a")</programlisting></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Collect</title>

        <para><programlisting>C-&gt;collect(c | &lt;expression with c&gt;)</programlisting>Collect
        iterates over the elements in the collection and collects together the
        result of evaluating the expression. The following collect expression
        add 1 to each element in the set:<programlisting>Set{1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9}-&gt;collect(x | x+1)</programlisting>Here
        is an example that collects together the names of the states in a
        state machine: context StateMachine<programlisting>@Operation allStateNames()
  states-&gt;collect(s | s.name)
end</programlisting></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Iterate</title>

        <para><programlisting>C-&gt;iterate(c acc = &lt;expression&gt; | &lt;expression with c and acc&gt;)</programlisting>The
        iterate operation is the most fundamental and general of the iterator
        operations. All other loop operations can be described as a special
        case of this operation. Like select and collect, an iterate has a
        iterator variable. In addition, it has an accumulator variable, which
        is given an initial value. The result of the iterate operation is the
        result of iterating over all the elements in the collection. For each
        successive element, the body expression is evaluated using the
        previous result of the accumulator. Here is an example of using
        iterate to add together a collection of numbers: <programlisting>Seq{1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10}-&gt;iterate(e s=0 | s + e)</programlisting>This
        sum() operation makes use of an iterate to sum a collection of
        integers: <programlisting>context Seq(Element)
@Operation sum()
  self-&gt;iterate(e sum=0 | sum + e)
end
</programlisting></para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Assignment</title>

    <para>In XOCL, values may be assigned to variables. The assignment keyword
    is “:=”. This should not confused with “=” which returns a Boolean
    value.</para>

    <para>The following code shows an assignment being used to set the name of
    a State by setting name to be x: <programlisting>Context Java
  @Operation createState (n:String):State
    let s = State() in
      s.name := n;
      s
    end
  end</programlisting>An assignment can be used to set global variables or
    local variables. When setting the value of a local attribute of a class,
    self.attname must be used as the target of the assignment. For instance,
    the following operation will set the name of the State to be
    x.<programlisting>context State
  @Operation setName(n)
    self.name := n
  end</programlisting>However, the following code will not be
    legal:<programlisting>context State
  @Operation setName(n)
    name := n
  end</programlisting></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Pattern Matching</title>

    <para>XOCL provides a powerful pattern matching language. This greatly
    simplifies the writing of pattern matching operations that would otherwise
    require a very imperative style of programming.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Patterns and Pattern Matching</title>

      <para>A pattern is matched against a value. The pattern match may
      succeed or fail in a given matching context. A matching context keeps
      track of any variable bindings generated by the match and maintains
      choice points for backtracking if the current match fails.</para>

      <para>Pattern matching can be viewed as being performed by a pattern
      matching engine that maintains the current pattern matching context as
      its state. The engine state consists of a stack of patterns to be
      matched against a stack of values, a collection of variable bindings and
      a stack of choice points. A choice point is a machine state. At any
      given time there is a pattern at the head of the pattern stack and a
      value at the head of the value stack. The machine executes by performing
      state transitions driven by the head of the pattern stack: if the outer
      structure of the pattern matches that of the value at the head of the
      value stack then:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>0 or more values are bound.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>0 or more choice points are added to the choice point
          stack.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>0 or more component patterns are pushed onto the pattern
          stack.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>0 or more component values are pushed onto the value
          stack.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the machine fails to match the pattern and value at the
          head of the respective stacks then the most recently created choice
          point is popped and becomes the new machine state. Execution
          continues until either the pattern stack is exhausted or the machine
          fails when the choice stack is empty.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Pattern Categories</title>

      <para>This section describes the different categories of pattern. The
      semantics of matching are defined informally in terms of a general
      description and example definitions involving the pattern.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Variables</title>

        <para>A variable pattern consists of a name, optionally another
        pattern and optionally a type. The simplest form of variable pattern
        is just a name, for example, the formal parameter x is a variable
        pattern:<programlisting>let add1 = @Operation(x) x + 1 end in ...</programlisting>Matching
        a simple variable pattern such as that shown above always succeeds and
        causes the name to be bound to the corresponding value. A variable may
        be qualified with a type declaration:<programlisting>let add1 = @Operation(x:Integer) x + 1 end in ...</programlisting>which
        has no effect on pattern matching. A variable may be qualified with a
        pattern as in x = &lt;Pattern&gt; where the pattern must occur before
        any type declaration. Such a qualified variable matches a value when
        the pattern also matches the value. Any variables in the pattern and x
        are bound in the process.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Constants</title>

        <para>A constant pattern is either a string, an integer, a boolean or
        an expression (in the case of an expression the pattern consists of [
        followed by an expression followed by ]). A constant pattern matches a
        value when the values is equal to the constant (in the case of an
        expression the matching process evaluates the expression each time the
        match occurs). For example:<programlisting>let fourArgs = @Operation(1,true,"three",x = [2 + 2]) x end in ...</programlisting>is
        an operation that succeeds in the case: <programlisting>fourArgs(1,true,"three",4)</programlisting>and
        returns 4.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Sequences</title>

        <para>A sequence pattern consists of either a pair of patterns or a
        sequence of patterns. In the case of a pair:<programlisting>let head = @Operation(Seq{head | tail}) head end in ...</programlisting>the
        pattern matches a non-empty sequence whose head must match the head
        pattern and whose tail must match the tail pattern. In the case of a
        sequence of patterns:<programlisting>let add3 = @Operation(Seq{x,y,z}) x + y + z end in ...</programlisting>the
        pattern matches a sequence of exactly the same size where each element
        matches the corresponding pattern.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Constructors</title>

        <para>A constructor pattern matches an object. A constructor pattern
        may be either a by-order-of-arguments constructor pattern (or
        BOA-constructor pattern) or a keyword constructor pattern. A
        BOA-constructor pattern is linked with the constructors of a class. It
        has the form:<programlisting>let flatten = @Operation(C(x,y,z)) Seq{x,y,z} end in ...</programlisting>where
        the class {\tt C} must define a 3-argument constructor. A
        BOA-constructor pattern matches an object when the object is an
        instance of the class (here {\tt C} but in general defined using a
        path) and when the object's slot values identified by the constructor
        of the class with the appropriate arity match the corresponding
        sub-patterns (here xy and z). A keyword constructor pattern has the
        form:<programlisting>let flatten = @Operation(C[name=y,age=x,address=y]) Seq{x,y,z} end in ...</programlisting>where
        the names of the slots are explicitly defined in any order (and may be
        repeated) .Such a pattern matches an object when it is an instance of
        the given class and when the values of the named slots match the
        appropriate sub-patterns.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Conditions</title>

        <para>A conditional pattern consists of a pattern and a predicate
        expression. It matches a value when the value matches the sub-pattern
        and when the expression evaluates to true in the resulting variable
        context. For example:<programlisting>let repeat = @Operation(Seq{x,y} when x = y) Seq{x} end in ...</programlisting>Note
        that the above example will fail (and probably throw an error
        depending on the context) if it is supplied with a pair whose values
        are different.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Sets</title>

        <para>Set patterns consist of an element pattern and a residual
        pattern. A set matches a pattern when an element can be chosen that
        matches the element pattern and where the rest of the set matches the
        residual pattern. For example:<programlisting>let choose = @Operation(S-&gt;including(x)) x end in ...</programlisting>which
        matches any non-empty set and selects a value from it at random. Set
        patterns introduce choice into the current context because often there
        is more than one way to choose a value from the set that matches the
        element pattern. For example:<programlisting>let chooseBigger = @Operation(S-&gt;including(x),y where x &gt; y) x end in ...</programlisting>Pattern
        matching in chooseBigger, for example:<programlisting>chooseBigger(Set{1,2,3},2)</programlisting>starts
        by selecting an element and binding it to x and binding S to the rest.
        In this case suppose that x = 1 and S = Set{2,3}. The pattern y
        matches and binds 2 and then the condition is applied. At this point,
        in general, there may be choices left in the context due to there
        being more than one element in the set supplied as the first
        parameter. If the condition x &gt; y fails then the matching process
        jumps to the most recent choice point (which in this cases causes the
        next element in the set to be chosen and bound to x). Suppose that 3
        is chosen this time; the condition is satisfied and the call returns3.
        The following is an example that sorts a set of integers into
        descending order:<programlisting>context Root
  @Operation sort(S)
    @Case S of
      Set{} do Seq{} end
      S-&gt;including(x) 
        when S-&gt;forAll(y | y &lt;= x) 
        do Seq{x | Q} where Q = sort(S) 
      end
    end
  end</programlisting></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Sequences</title>

        <para>Sequence patterns use the infix + operator to combine two
        patterns that match against two sub-sequences. For example the
        following operation removes a sequence of 0's occurring in a
        sequence:<programlisting>context Root
  @Operation remove0s(x) 
    @Case x of 
      (S1 when S1-&gt;forAll(x | x &lt;&gt; 0)) + 
        (S2 when S2-&gt;forAll(x | x = 0)) + 
        (S3 when S3-&gt;forAll(x | x &lt;&gt; 0)) 
      do S1 + S3 
      end 
    end
  end</programlisting></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Syntax</title>

        <para>Syntax patterns consist of expressions within quasi-quotes [|
        and |]. The quotes are a short-hand for writing out the equivalent
        constructor patterns. Syntax patterns provide a powerful way of
        constructing syntax mappings where the pattern is defined in terms of
        concrete syntax rather than the equivalent abstract syntax structures.
        Consider an operation that extracts the body of a
        letexpression:<programlisting>context Root
  @Operation getBody([| let x = value in body end |]) 
    body 
  end</programlisting>Unfortunately, this will not work as you may expect
        since the syntax pattern states that the operation expects to be
        supplied with a let expression that consists of exactly one binding
        and where the body of the expression is the variable whose name is
        body. We wish to place patterns within the syntax construct that match
        against specific elements of the abstract syntax structure. To do this
        we use pattern-unquotes:<programlisting>context Root
  @Operation getBody([| let &lt;| bindings |&gt; in &lt;| body |&gt; end |]) 
    body 
   end</programlisting>Within a syntax pattern the unquotes &lt;| and |&gt;
        are used to surround patterns that are to be matched against the
        abstract syntax structures occurring at that point in the supplied
        expression. In the example above, bindings is bound to the sequence of
        bindings in the let and body is bound to the body. The following
        example shows an operation that calculates the free variables
        occurring in an expression. The expression is limited to a small
        number of XOCL expressions: <programlisting>context Root
  @Operation FV(e)
    @Case e of 
      [| let &lt;| Seq{} |&gt; in &lt;| e |&gt; end |] do 
         FV(e) 
         end
      [| let &lt;| Seq{ ValueBinding(v,e1) | bs } |&gt;
         in &lt;| e2 |&gt; 
         end
      |] do
         FV([| let &lt;bs&gt; in &lt;e2&gt; end|])-&gt;excluding(v)
         end
      [| if &lt;| e1 |&gt; 
         then &lt;| e2 |&gt;
         else &lt;| e3 |&gt; 
         end 
      |] do
         FV(e1) + FV(e2) + FV(e3)
      end
      [| &lt;| e1 |&gt; = &lt;| e2 |&gt; |] do
         FV(e1) + FV(e2)
      end
      Var[name=n] do 
         Set{n} 
      end
    end
  end</programlisting>The following call:<programlisting>FV[| let x = 10; y = 20 in if x = y then z else a end end |])</programlisting>produces
        the set <programlisting>Set{a,z}</programlisting></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Pattern Contexts</title>

      <para>Patterns may be used in the following contexts:</para>

      <para>Operation Parameters. Each parameter in an operation definition is
      a pattern. Parameter patterns are useful when defining an operation that
      must deconstruct one or more values passed as arguments. Note that if
      the pattern match fails then the operation invocation will raise an
      error. Operations defined in the same class and with the same name are
      merged into a single operation in which each operation is tried in turn
      when the operation is called via an instance of the class. Therefore in
      the following example:<programlisting>@Class P
   @Operation f(Seq{}) 0 end
   @Operation f(Seq{x | t}) x + self.f(t) end
end</programlisting>an instance of P has a single operation f that adds up all
      the elements of a sequence.</para>

      <para>Case Arms. A case expression consists of a number of arms each of
      which has a sequence of patterns and an expression. A case expression
      dispatches on a sequence of values and attempts to match them against
      the corresponding patterns in each arm in turn. For example, suppose we
      want to calculate the set of duplicated elements in a pair of
      sets:<programlisting>context Root
   @Operation dups(s1,s2)
     @Case s1,s2 of
         s1-&gt;including(x),s2-&gt;including(y) when x = y do 
            Set{x} + dups(s1,s2) 
         end
         s1-&gt;including(x),s2 do 
           dups(s1,s2) 
         end
         s1,s2-&gt;including(y) do 
            dups(s1,s2) 
         end
         Set{},Set{} do 
            Set{} 
         end
     end
   end</programlisting>In XMap transformations, as described in the XMap
      manual.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Data Type Operations</title>

    <para></para>

    <section>
      <title>Boolean</title>

      <para>A value of the Boolean type can either be true or false.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Operators</title>

        <para>All the usual Boolean operators are provided.</para>

        <table>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>Operators</emphasis>
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  <emphasis>Syntax</emphasis>
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  <emphasis>Result Type</emphasis>
                </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Or</entry>

                <entry>a or b</entry>

                <entry>Boolean</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>And</entry>

                <entry>a and b</entry>

                <entry>Boolean</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>negation</entry>

                <entry>not b</entry>

                <entry>Boolean</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>equals</entry>

                <entry>a = b</entry>

                <entry>Boolean</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>not equals</entry>

                <entry>a &lt;&gt; b</entry>

                <entry>Boolean</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>implies</entry>

                <entry>a implies b</entry>

                <entry>Boolean</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Examples</title>

        <para><programlisting>not true
balance &gt; 0 or balance &lt; 100
x &lt;&gt; y implies x.name &lt;&gt; y.name</programlisting>The following
        example shows the definition of the logical operator and. It uses an
        if statement to test whether other is a Boolean value and if it is
        returns the conjunct of self and other. An error is reported if the
        type is incorrect.</para>

        <para><programlisting>context Boolean
@Operation booland(other)
      if other.isKindOf(Boolean)
      then
        self and other
      else
        self.error("Boolean::booland expects a boolean " + other.toString())
      end
    end</programlisting></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Channels</title>

      <para>XOCL provides channels to perform input and output. The channel
      classes are defined in the IO package and are defined in a separate
      document. This section provides a very brief overview of input and
      output using channels.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Standard Input and Output</title>

        <para>XOCL provides two channels as global variables defined in the
        name space Root. The output channel stdout is used to send characters
        to the standard output. The input channel stdin reads characters from
        the standard input. In both cases characters are represented as
        integer character codes in the range 0 to 255. Characters are written
        on output channels by outch.write(c) and read from input channels by
        inch.read().</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Formatting Output</title>

        <para>XOCL provides a convenient means for formatting output to
        channels. The global variable format is bound to a character formatter
        that is used as an operation by applying it to arguments that control
        the output of characters. The general form is:<programlisting>format(outch,formatString,args)</programlisting>where
        the format string is a string of characters controlling how the
        sequence of argument values is formatted as output to the output
        channel. A format string is a sequence of characters and format
        directives. Each character occurring in a format string is written to
        the output channel in sequence. A format directive starts with the
        tilde (~) character and controls how the output is written and how the
        fomat arguments are consumed and written to the output channel. A
        typical use of format will print a message followed by a newline. A
        newline is produced using the format directive ~% as
        in:<programlisting>format(outch,”hello world~%”,Seq{})</programlisting>Note
        that there are no format arguments in the example above. Where there
        are no format args, they can be omitted: <programlisting>format(outch,”hello world~%”)</programlisting>The
        directive ~S consumes the next format argument, translates it to a
        string and prints it to the output channel. For example, if we want to
        print out the source and target of an edge with an arrow between them:
        <programlisting>format(outch,”~S -&gt; ~S~%”,Seq{edge.source,edge.target})</programlisting>Format
        defines many other directives that are defined in the XMF guide to
        IO.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>File Based Input and Output</title>

        <para>The IO package of XMF provides file channels for accessing and
        updating files. These channels are defined in the XMF guide to IO. A
        useful special form is provided that hides the details of file
        IO:<programlisting>@WithOpenFile(inch &lt;- filename)
  // Use inch.read() to read characters from the file.
  // inch.read() returns -1 when EOF is reached.
end</programlisting><programlisting>@WithOpenFile(outch -&gt; filename)
  // Use outch in format expressions to write characters to the file.
end</programlisting>In both of the examples above the filename is specified as
        an expression whose value is a string. The channels used to perform
        the input and output are automatically closed when the WithOpenFile
        expression completes. If an IO error occurs during the evaluation of
        the WithOpenFile then XOCL guarantees that the channels are closed
        before the error is reported.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Clients</title>

      <para>XOCL provides clients that can be used to connect to external
      servers on ports and then communicate via input output channels with the
      server.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Daemons</title>

      <para>An XOCL daemon is an operation that is attached to an object’s
      slot such that whenever the slot changes state the operation is invoked.
      The invocation is referred to as firing the daemon. There are several
      different types of daemon depending on the required firing mode: whether
      the operation is invoked when any change occurs, when a new value is
      added to the slot or when a value is removed from the slot.</para>

      <para>A new daemon is created using the Daemon
      constructor:<programlisting>Daemon(id,type,slot,action,persistent,traced,target)</programlisting>Where
      id is any XOCL value and is used to identify the daemon in a given
      context; type is an integer determining the firing mode of the daemon;
      slot is a symbol that names the slot that is being monitored by the
      daemon (or null if this is not appropriate); action is an operation to
      be invoked when the daemon fires; persistent is a boolean value
      determining whether or not the daemon will be saved when an object
      containing the daemon is saved to a XAR file; traced is a boolean value
      that determines whether or not tracing information is printed when the
      daemon fires; target is any XOCL value and provides a means of
      associating state with a daemon.</para>

      <para>The type of the daemon is supplied as an integer value. The types
      are defined by an enumerated type defined in the class Daemon; the type
      determines the number of arguments that the action should have. The
      following table lists the types and provides skeleton operations of the
      appropriate form for the daemon type:</para>

      <para><table>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Type</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
				<entry>Action Skeleton</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>XCore::Daemon::ANY</entry>
                <entry>Any change to the object will fire the daemon. The action is supplied with the object, the name of the slot that changes, the new value and the old value of the slot. The value of slot in the construction of the daemon is null.</entry>
				<entry>@Operation(object,slot,newValue,oldValue) … end</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>XCore::Daemon::VALUE</entry>
                <entry>Any change to the named slot will fire the daemon.</entry>
				<entry>@Operation(object,slot,newValue,oldValue) … end</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>XCore::Daemon::ADD</entry>
                <entry>The slot must contain a set or sequence. When a new value is added to the set or sequence the daemon will fire. The action is supplied with the added value.</entry>
				<entry>@Operation(object,slot,value) … end</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>XCore::Daemon::REMOVE</entry>
                <entry>The slot must contain a set or sequence. When a value is removed from the set or sequence the daemon will fire. The action is supplied with the removed value.</entry>
				<entry>@Operation(object,slot,value) … end</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Elements</title>

      <para>All XOCL values are instances of the XCore class named Element.
      The operations defined by this class are available for all values in
      XMF-Mosaic. The following table shows the essential operations defined
      by this class. Note that XOCl is a dynamic language and new operations
      can be added to a class at any time. Adding operations to Element will
      cause these to be available for all values.</para>

      <para><table>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>copy():Element</entry>

                <entry>Returns a copy of the receiver. By default this returns the receiver. Sub-classes o Element may redefine this appropriately.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>equals(other:Element):Boolean</entry>

                <entry>Returns true when the receiver is equal to the argument. By default this is defined to be true when the identify (memory location) of elements with state are the same. Strings are compared character by character. Sets are equal when all elements are equal.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>error(reason:String)</entry>

                <entry>A convenient way of raising an error exception.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>hashCode():Integer</entry>

                <entry>Returns the code used to index into hash tables.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>init(args:Seq(Element)):Element</entry>

                <entry>All elements can be initialised with respect to arguments. See Object for more specific information.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>isKindOf(c:Classifier):Boolean</entry>

                <entry>Returns true when the receiver is an instance (dorect or otherwise) of the argument. Note that null is considered an instance of everything.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>isReallyKindOf(classifier:Classifier):Boolean</entry>

                <entry>True when isKindOf is true and the receiver is not null.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>of():Classifier</entry>

                <entry>Returns the direct classifier of the receiver.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>send(message:String,args:Seq(Element)):Element
                </entry>

                <entry>Sends the supplied message with the given arguments to the receiver. Returns the result.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>toString():String</entry>

                <entry>Produces a string representation of the receiver. The system uses toString to display XOCL values in all circumstances. It is usual to provide an appropriate definition of toString in all class definitions. This aids debugging systems.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>yield()</entry>

                <entry>Halt the current thread and reschedule it.</entry>
              </row>

            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Integers</title>

      <para>This is the data type for integer values The default value is
      0.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Operators</title>

        <para>All the usual operators on Integer types are provided.</para>

        <para><table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Operator</entry>
                  <entry>Syntax</entry>
                  <entry>Result Type</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>equals</entry>
                  <entry>a = b</entry>
                  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>not equals</entry>
                  <entry>a &lt;&gt; b</entry>
                  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>less than</entry>
                  <entry>a &lt; b</entry>
                  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>more than</entry>
                  <entry>a &gt; b</entry>
                  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>less or equal</entry>
                  <entry>a &lt;= b</entry>
                  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>more or equal</entry>
                  <entry>a &gt;= b</entry>
                  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>plus</entry>
                  <entry>a + b</entry>
                  <entry>Integer or Float</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>minus</entry>
                  <entry>a - b</entry>
                  <entry>Integer or Float</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>multiplication</entry>
                  <entry>a * b</entry>
                  <entry>Integer or Float</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>divison</entry>
                  <entry>a / b</entry>
                  <entry>Integer or Float</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>operation</entry>
                  <entry>a.op()</entry>
                  <entry>Element</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Operations</title>

        <para>A variety of integer operations are also provided.</para>

        <para><table>
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>abs():Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the absolute value of an integer. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>add(other:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Adds an integer to another integer of a float. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>asSeq():Seq(Integer)</entry>
                  <entry>Turns an integer into a 24 bit sequence of binary values. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>bit(index:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the ith bit after converting an integer into a 24 bit sequence of binary values. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>byte(index:Integer):Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the byte of an indexed by index. Bytes are indexed from 1 (low) to 4 (high). </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>div(other:Integer):Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Integer division returns the number of times an integer can be divided by other a whole number of times. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>floor():Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Rounds a float down to an integer. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>greater(other:Integer):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if an integer is greater than other. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>isAlphaChar():Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if an integer is a valid alphanumeric value. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>isLowerCaseChar():Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if an integer is a valid lower case alphanumeric value. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>isNewLineChar():Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if an integer is the new line alphanumeric value.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>isNumericChar():Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if an integer is a valid numeric alphanumeric value. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>isUpperCaseChar():Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if an integer is a valid upper case alphanumeric value. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>isWhiteSpaceChar():Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if an integer is the white space alphanumeric value. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>less(other:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if the integer is lower than other. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>lsh(n:Integer):Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Left shift bit operation.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>max(other:Integer):Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Compares an integer with other and returns the maximum value. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>min(other:Integer):Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Compares an integer with other and returns the minimum value. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>mod(other:Integer):Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the remainder when an integer is divided by other. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>mul(other:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Multiples an integer by other. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>round():Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Rounds a float to the nearest whole integer. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>rsh(n:Integer):Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Right shift bit operation.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>slash(other:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Divides an integer by other. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>sqrt():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the square root of an integer.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>sub(other:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Substracts other from an integer.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>to(n:Integer):Seq(Integer)</entry>
                  <entry>Generates a sequence of integers from self to n.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>toString():String</entry>
                  <entry>Converts an integer to a string.</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Examples</title>

        <para><programlisting>13 * 42 = 546
12 &gt; 10 = false
12.max(11) = 12
12.min(11) = 11
12.mod(5) = 2
1.to(3) = Seq{1,2,3}</programlisting>The following example shows an operator
        definition for factorial. The operator is named fact, takes a single
        argument n and is defined in the global context Root which means that
        the name fact is available everywhere: <programlisting>context Root
  @Operation fact(n)
    if n = 0
    then 1
    else n * fact(n - 1)
    end
  end</programlisting>Another example of a global operation definition is gcd
        below that computes the greatest common divisor for a pair of positive
        integers. The example shows that operations can optionally have
        argument and return types: <programlisting>context Root
  @Operation gcd(m:Integer,n:Integer):Integer
    if m = n
    then n
    else
      if m &gt; n
      then gcd(m-n,n)
      else gcd(m,n-m)
      end
    end
  end</programlisting></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Floats</title>

      <para>The data type for real values. The default value is 0.0.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Operators</title>

        <para><table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Operator</entry>
				  <entry>Syntax</entry>
				  <entry>Result Type</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>equals</entry>
				  <entry>a = b</entry>
				  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>not equals</entry>
				  <entry>a &lt;&gt; b</entry>
				  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>less than</entry>
				  <entry>a &lt; b</entry>
				  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>more than</entry>
				  <entry>a &gt; b</entry>
				  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>less or equal</entry>
				  <entry>a &lt;= b</entry>
				  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>more or equal</entry>
				  <entry>a &gt;=</entry>
				  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>plus</entry>
				  <entry>a + b</entry>
				  <entry>Integer or Float</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>minus</entry>
				  <entry>a - b</entry>
				  <entry>Integer or Float</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>multiplication</entry>
				  <entry>a * b</entry>
				  <entry>Integer or Float</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>division</entry>
				  <entry>a/b</entry>
				  <entry>Integer or Float</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>operation</entry>
				  <entry>a.op()</entry>
				  <entry>Element</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Operations</title>

        <para><table>
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>abs():Float</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the absolute value of a float. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>add(other:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Adds a float to other.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>cos():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the cosine of a float.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>div(other:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Divides a rounded float by the result of rounding other. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>floor():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Rounds a float down to an integer. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>greater(other:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a float is greater than other. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>init(args:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>No Documentation Specified</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>less(other:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a float is less than other. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>max(other:Integer):Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Compares a float with other and returns the maximum value. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>min(other:Integer):Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Compares a float with other and returns the minimum value.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>mod(other:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns a float modulo other after rounding down to integers. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>mul(other:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Multiply a float by other.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>round():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the result of rounding a float down. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>sin():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the sin() of a float.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>slash(other:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Divided a float by other.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>sqrt():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the square root of a float.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>sub(other:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Subtracts an integer from a float.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>toString():String</entry>
                  <entry>Converts and integer to a string.</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Examples</title>

        <para><programlisting>1.1 &gt; 1.01 = true
3.5.round() = 4
3.2.floor() = 3
13.sqrt() = 3.6055512</programlisting>The following operation defines the
        operation abs(). If the float is a negative number it is subtracted
        from 0, otherwise the value of the float is returned.<programlisting>@Operation abs():Float
      if self &lt; 0
      then
        0 - self
      else
        self
      end
    end</programlisting></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Objects</title>

      <para>XOCL objects are XCore elements with slots. A slot is an
      association between a name (symbol) and a value. A slot has state and
      can be updated. All objects in XMF-Mosaic are instances of classes that
      inherit from the XCore class Object. The essential operations supported
      by Object are defined below:</para>

      <table>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>addDaemon(d:Daemon)</entry>
              <entry>All objects have a collection of daemons. A daemon is an operation that is invoked whenever a slot of the object is updated </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>daemons():Seq(Daemon)</entry>
              <entry>Returns the currently defined daemons for the receiver. Daemons are fired when the object changes state and when the objects daemons are active. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>daemonsActive():Boolean</entry>
              <entry>Returns whether or not the daemons of this object will be fired when an update takes place.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>get(name:String)</entry>
              <entry>Returns the value of the named slot of the receiver. The name may be a string or a symbol. An exception is raised if the receiver has no slot with the given name.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>getStructuralFeatureNames():Set(String)</entry>
              <entry>Returns the slot names of the object. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>hasDaemonWithId(id:Element):Boolean</entry>
              <entry>Returns true when the receiver has a daemon with the supplied id.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>hasSlot(name:Element):Boolean</entry>
              <entry>Returns true when the receiver has a slot with the given name. The name may be a string or a symbol.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>init(args:Element)</entry>
              <entry>When an object is initialised, by default we look for a constructor that has the same arity as the supplied arguments. If we find one then it is invoked. This operation causes constructors to be invoked when they are defined for the class of the receiver. If this operation is redefined then you should use super(args) in the sub-class to invoke this operation.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>removeDaemon(d:Daemon)</entry>
              <entry>Removes the supplied daemon.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>set(name:String,value:Element)</entry>
              <entry>Sets the named slot to the supplied value in the receiver. Raises an exception if the receiver has no slot with the supplied name. The name may be a symbol or a string.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>setDaemons(daemons:Seq(Daemon))</entry>
              <entry>Updates the daemons of the receiver to be the supplied sequence.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>setDaemonsActive(active:Boolean)</entry>
              <entry>Sets whether or not the daemons of this receiver will be fired when an update takes place</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Null</title>

      <para>The value null is an instance of the XCore class Null and is
      considered special in the sense that it can be viewed as the undefined
      value. It is an instance of all classes in XMF and is the default value
      of all slots whose type is not a basic type (such as String) or a set or
      sequence. There is only one null value and it is only equal to
      itself.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Operations</title>

      <para>XOCL operations are used to implement both procedures and
      functions (queries). An operation has an optional name, some parameters,
      a return type and a body. Operations are objects with internal state;
      part of the internal state is the name, parameter information, type and
      body. Operations also have property lists that can be used to attach
      information to the operation for use by XOCL programs.</para>

      <para>Operations can be created and stored in XMF data items. In
      particular, operations can be added to name spaces and then referenced
      via the name space (either where the name space is imported or directly
      by giving the path to the operation). We have seen many examples of
      adding operations to the name space called Root in earlier parts of this
      primer. The syntax:<programlisting>context Root
  @Operation add(x,y) x + y end</programlisting>can occur at the top-level of
      an XMF source file, compiled and loaded. It is equivalent to the
      following expression:<programlisting>Root.add(@Operation add(x,y) x + y end);</programlisting>Unlike
      the context expression, the call to add may occur anywhere in XMF
      code.</para>

      <para>Operations are performed by sending them a message invoke with two
      arguments: the value of self (or target) to be used in the body of the
      operation and a sequence of argument values. The target of the
      invocation is important because it provides the value of self in the
      body of the operation and supplies the values of the slot-bound
      variables. The add operation can be invoked by:<programlisting>add.invoke(null,Seq{1,2})</programlisting>It
      produces the value 3. Note that in this case there is no reference to
      selfor slot-bound variables in the body and therefore the target of the
      invocation is null. A shorthand for invocation is provided:
      add(1,2)</para>

      <para>However, note that no target can be supplied with the shorthand.
      In this case the target will default to the value of self that was in
      scope when the operation was created.</para>

      <para>Locally bound variables that are scoped over an operation are
      available within the body of the operation event though the operation is
      returned from the lexical context. This is often referred to as closing
      the local variable into the operation (or closure). This feature is very
      useful when generating behaviour that differs only in terms of context.
      Suppose that transition machine states have an action that is
      implemented as an operation and that the action is to be performed when
      the state is entered:<programlisting>context StateMachines
  @Class State
    @Attribute name : String end
    @Attribute action : Operation end
    @Constructor(name,action) end
    @Operation enter()
      action()
    end
  end</programlisting>Compiled operations have the following slots:</para>

      <para><table>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>arity</entry>
                <entry>Integer</entry>
				<entry>The number of arguments required by the operation.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>codeBox</entry>
                <entry>Element</entry>
				<entry>The XVM instructions.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>dynamics</entry>
                <entry>Seq(element)</entry>
				<entry>The global variables available via imports.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>globals</entry>
                <entry>Seq(Element)</entry>
				<entry>The global variables available via imports.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>isVarArgs</entry>
                <entry>Boolean</entry>
				<entry>Whether this operation can take a variable number of arguments.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>properties</entry>
                <entry>Seq(Element)</entry>
				<entry>A sequence of name value pairs.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>sig</entry>
                <entry>Seq(Element)</entry>
				<entry>A type signature for the operation.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>supers</entry>
                <entry>Seq(Operation)</entry>
				<entry>A sequence of operations headed by the owner of the slot. Used when invoking super.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>target</entry>
                <entry>Element</entry>
				<entry>Value used as self within the operation.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>traced</entry>
                <entry>Operation</entry>
				<entry>An operation used as a proxy when the operation is traced. (null is not traced).</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></para>

      <section>
        <title>Operations</title>

        <para>Compiled operation defines the following operations:</para>

        <para><table>
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>addDaemon(daemon:Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Operations have daemons that monitor their slots.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>addNameChangedDaemon(d:Element,actionSource:Element) </entry>
				  <entry>Use this operation to add a daemon that monitors the name of a compiled operation for changes. The args for the daemon are the new name and the old name.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>arity():Integer</entry>
				  <entry>The number of arguments expected by the operation. Use this rather than reference the slot.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>daemons():Seq(Operation)</entry>
				  <entry>Returns the daemons currently monitoring the operation.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>disassemble():String</entry>
				  <entry>Displays the XVM instructions to stdout.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>disassemble(out:Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Displays the XVM instructions to out.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>doc():Element</entry>
				  <entry>Any documentation defined for the receiver.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>get(name:String):Element</entry>
				  <entry>Reference a named slot of the receiver.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>getStructuralFeatureNames():Set(String)</entry>
				  <entry>Get the slots defined for the receiver.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>hasProperty(property:Element):Boolean</entry>
				  <entry>Returns true when the receiver has the supplied property.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>hasSlot(name:String):Boolean</entry>
				  <entry>Returns true when the receiver has the supplied name.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>importNameSpace(n:NameSpace)</entry>
				  <entry>Imports the supplied name space and its contents to the receiver. If the name space is already imported then no change is made. Otherwise the name space is added as the most specific imported name space.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>importNameSpaces(N:Seq(NameSpace))</entry>
				  <entry>Imports the sequence of name spaces in the order that they are supplied.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>imports(n:NameSpace):Boolean</entry>
				  <entry>Returns true when the receiver imports the supplied name space.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>imports():Seq(NameSpace)</entry>
				  <entry>Returns the sequence of imported name spaces.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>isVarArgs():Boolean</entry>
				  <entry>returns true when the receiver can be supplied with a variable number of arguments. Use this in preference to referencing the slot.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>name():Symbol</entry>
				  <entry>Returns the name of the receiver. Use this in preference to referencing the slot.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>owner():Element</entry>
				  <entry>Returns the owner of the receiver. Use this in preference to referencing the slot.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>paramNames():Seq(String)</entry>
				  <entry>Returns the sequence of parameter names.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>paramTypes():Seq(Classifier)</entry>
				  <entry>Returns the sequence of parameter types.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>properties():Element</entry>
				  <entry>Returns the receivers property list.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>property(property:Element):Element</entry>
				  <entry>Returns the value of the supplied property.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>removeDaemon(daemon:Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Removes the supplied daemon.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>set(name:String,value:Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Sets the supplied slot.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>setArity(arity:Element) </entry>
				  <entry>Changes the arity (don’t use).</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>setDaemons(daemons:Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Sets the daemons.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>setDoc(doc:Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Sets the documentation.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>setName(name:Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Sets the name.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>setOwner(owner:Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Sets the owner.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>setProperties(properties:Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Sets the properties.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>setProperty(property:Element,value:Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Sets the property.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>setSig(sig:Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Sets the type signature.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>setSource(source:String)</entry>
				  <entry>Sets the source code string.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>setSupers(supers:Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Sets the supers list.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>setTarget(target:Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Sets the target.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>sig():Seq(Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Returns the type signature.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>source():String</entry>
				  <entry>Returns the source code string.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>supers():Seq(Operation)</entry>
				  <entry>Returns the supers list.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>target():Element</entry>
				  <entry>Returns the target.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>trace():Operation</entry>
				  <entry>Returns the trace operation.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>traced():Boolean</entry>
				  <entry>True when the receiver is traced.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>type():Classifier</entry>
				  <entry>Returns the return type.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>untrace()</entry>
				  <entry>Stops printing trace information when the receiver is invoked.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>update(newOp:Element)</entry>
				  <entry>Replaces the receiver with the argument. The update is performed in place so that all references to the receiver are also updated.</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Strings</title>

      <para>A string is a sequence of characters. Literal strings are written
      in enclosing double string quotes, such as “fred” and “fido”.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Operators</title>

        <para>Strings can be compared using equals (=) and can be
        concatenated.</para>

        <para><table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Operator</entry>
                  <entry>Syntax</entry>
				  <entry>Result Type</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>equals</entry>
                  <entry>a = b</entry>
				  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>not equals</entry>
                  <entry>a &lt;&gt; b</entry>
				  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>concatenate</entry>
                  <entry>a + b</entry>
				  <entry>String</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>operation</entry>
                  <entry>a.op()</entry>
				  <entry>Element</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>Strings can also be compared using &lt;, &lt;=, &gt; and
        &gt;= in which case the usual lexicographic ordering applies.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Operations</title>

        <para>A large number of string operations are provided for
        manipulating strings. These are given below.</para>

        <para><table>
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>asBool():Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Converts a string into a Boolean provided it has the string value true or false. String can be lower or upper case. An exception is raised if the string is invalid.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>asFloat():Float</entry>
                  <entry>Converts a string into a Float. It splits the string on its decimal point, converts the two strings into integers and passes them to the Float constructor. An exception is raised if the result is not a Float.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>asHTML():String</entry>
                  <entry>Transforms a string literal to HTML replacing any illegal HTML characters so that the string is faithfully printed.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>asInt():Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Converts a string into an Integer. Raises an exception if it cannot be converted.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>asSeq():Seq(Integer)</entry>
                  <entry>Converts a string into a sequence of character codes.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>asSet():Set(Integer)</entry>
                  <entry>Converts a string into a set of character codes</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>asSymbol():Symbol</entry>
                  <entry>Converts a string into a Symbol. In general, symbols can be processed more efficiently than strings, e.g. as indexes in table lookups.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>at(i:Integer):Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the ith character in a string starting from position 0.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>default():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the default value for a string: the empty string</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>deleteFile():Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Deletes the file given by a string path. Raises an exception if the file does not exist or cannot be deleted.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>drop(n:Integer):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Removes the first i elements from a string.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>edit():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Launches an editor for a string.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>escapeCharsToNewLines():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Substitutes escape characters in a string for new lines.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>exec(args:Seq(String)):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Currently not supported.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>fileExists():Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if the file given by a string path exists, otherwise false.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>fileSize():Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the size of a file given by a string path.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>greater(other:String):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a string is greater than the supplied string. The strings are compared alphabetically.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>hasPrefix(prefix:String):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a string is prefixed by the string, prefix.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>hasSuffix(suffix:String):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a string has a suffix, suffix.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>indexOf(char:String):Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the index of a character, char in a string.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>isOlder(file:String):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Compares the last modified date of the file referenced by a string path with file. Returns true if file is older.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>less(other:String):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a string is less than the supplied string. The strings are compared alphabetically. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>loadBin(verbose:Boolean):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Load the binary for the file referenced by a string path. Displays loading information if verbose is true. Raises an exception if it does not exist.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>lookup():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the value of the dynamic variable with the name defined by self or raises an error otherwise.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>lowerCaseInitialLetter():String</entry>
                  <entry>Makes the first letter of a string lower case.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>mkDir():Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Creates a directory. Returns true when the directory already exists or is successfully created. Returns false when the directory cannot be created.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>newLinesToEscapeChars():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Substitutes new lines in a string for escape characters.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>padFrom(width:Integer,char:Integer):String</entry>
                  <entry>Pads ups to a string with additional character codes up to width</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>padTo(width:Integer,char:Integer):String</entry>
                  <entry>Pads after a string with additional character codes up to width.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>parentDir():String</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the parent directory of the file referenced by a string path. Returns an exception if it cannot be found.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>readFile():String</entry>
                  <entry>Reads the file referenced by a string path, provided that it exists.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>renameFile(newName:String):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Renames a file referenced by a string path. A rename is only performed if the file exists and there doesnt exist a file with the new name.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>repeat(n:Integer):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Duplicates a string the given number of times.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>reverse():String</entry>
                  <entry>Reverses the characters in a string. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>size():Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the size of a string.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>splitBy(chars:String,start:Integer,last:Integer):Seq(String)</entry>
                  <entry>Splits a string into a sequence of strings around some characters. The variables start and last can be used to filter the returned string by returning the characters from start to last. Setting start and last to 0 will return the whole string.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>stripNonAlphaChars():String</entry>
                  <entry>Strips all non-alphanumeric characters from a string.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>stripWhiteSpace():String</entry>
                  <entry>Strips any whitespaces from a string.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>subString(firstChar:String,pastLastChar:String):String</entry>
                  <entry>Uses indices to chop up a string. The first index is the starting character and the second index is 1+ the final character.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>subst(new:String,old:String,all:Boolean):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Substitutes the string old in a string with new. If all is set to false, just replaces the first occurence. If true replaces them all.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>toLower():String</entry>
                  <entry>Converts all characters in a string to lower case.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>toString():String</entry>
                  <entry>Prints a string.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>toUpper():String</entry>
                  <entry>Converts all characters in a string to upper case.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>truncate(width:Integer):String</entry>
                  <entry>Truncates a string by width characters.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>upperCaseInitialLetter():String</entry>
                  <entry>Makes the first letter of a string upper case.</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Examples</title>

        <para><programlisting>"to" + "day" = "today"
"tomorrow".size() = 8
"UPPER".toLower() = "upper"
"lower".toUpper() = "LOWER"
"Ceteva".subString(0,4) = "Ceta"
"lower" &lt;&gt; "LOWER" = true
"123.456".splitBy(".",0,0) = Seq{"123","456"}</programlisting>Characters are
        represented as integer ASCII codes. The following operation checks
        whether a string starts with an upper case character:<programlisting>context Root
@Operation startsUpperCase(s:String):Boolean
  if s-&gt;size &gt; 0
  then
    let c = s-&gt;at(0)
    in "A"-&gt;at(0) &lt;= c and c &lt;= "Z"-&gt;at(0)
    end
  else false
  end
end</programlisting></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sequences</title>

      <para>A sequence is a list of values that may have duplicates. A
      sequence literal is denoted by enumerating the elements in a Seq{}. For
      example, a sequence of numbers: Seq{1,2,3}. Sequences can be nested, for
      example: Seq{Seq{“a”,”b”},1}.</para>

      <para>The default value of a sequence is the empty sequence, Seq{}. A
      Seq(Element) is an instance of the Sequence type. It contains the
      elements in the sequence.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Operators</title>

        <para>Two sequences can be tested for equality and inequality. Two
        sequences are equal provides that they contain the same elements in
        the same order. Sequences can be concatenated.</para>

        <para><table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Operator</entry>
                  <entry>Syntax</entry>
                  <entry>Result Type</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>equals</entry>
                  <entry>a = b</entry>
                  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>not equals</entry>
                  <entry>a &lt;&gt; b</entry>
                  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>concatenation</entry>
                  <entry>a + b</entry>
                  <entry>Sequence(Element)</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Operations</title>

        <para>XOCL provides a large number of sequence operations, including
        all those support by standard OCL.</para>

        <para><table>
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>append(s:Seq(Element)):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Append two sequences.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>asProperSeq():Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>No Documentation Specified</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>asSeq():Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Turns a sequence into a sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>asSet():Set(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Turn a sequence into a set.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>asString():String</entry>
                  <entry>Turns a sequence of integers into a string.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>asVector():Vector</entry>
                  <entry>Turns a sequence into a vector.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>at(n:Integer):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the nth element of a sequence starting from 0.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>bind(key:Element,value:Element):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Binds a key with a value and adds it to the head of the sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>binds(key:Element):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true of a sequence contains a binding that matches the key/</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>butLast():Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns all elements but the last element.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>contains(element:Element):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if the sequence contains the element.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>default():Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the default sequence: an empty sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>dot(name:String):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the result of iterating over a sequence and performing dot on each element.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>drop(n:Integer):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Drops the first n elements from a sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>equals(other:Element):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a sequence equals another sequence. To be equal they must both be sequences and their elements should be equal and in the same order.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>excluding(element:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns all elements in the sequence excluding element.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>exists(pred:Element):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true when one element of the sequence satisfies the predicate otherwise it returns false.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>flatten():Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Turns a sequence of sequences of X into a sequence of X. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>forAll(pred:Element):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if all elements of the sequence satisfy the predicate otherwise returns false.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>hasPrefix(prefix:Seq(Element)):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a sequence is prefixed by the sequence prefix.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>hasSuffix(suffix:Seq(Element)):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a sequence is suffixed by the sequence suffix</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>head():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the head of a sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>includes(element:Element):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a sequence contains element. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>includesAll(c:Collection(Element)):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a sequence includes all the elements in the collection c.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>including(e:Element):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the result of including the element e in a sequence. The element is added to the head of the sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>indexOf(element:Element):Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the first index of the element in a sequence. If it is not found, returns -1.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>insertAt(e:Element,i:Integer):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Inserts an element e at position i in a sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>inspectDialog(level:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>No Documentation Specified</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>isEmpty():Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a sequence is empty.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>isKindOf(type:Classifier):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if all elements in a sequence are instances of type.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>isProperSequence():Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if the last tail is a valid sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>iter(iterator:Element,value:Element):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Iterates through a sequence, returning a sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>last():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the last element of a non-empty sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>linkAt(element:Element,index:Integer):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the last element of a non-empty sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>lookup(key:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Looks up a pair in a sequence using the key. Returns an error if the key cannot be found.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>max():Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the maximum valued element in the sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>mul(s:Seq(Element)):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Generates a sequence containing all combinations of elements in the two sequences.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>prefixes():Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns all possible prefixes of a sequence including the empty sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>prepend(e:Element):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Prepend adds an element to the head of a sequence and returns a new sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>qsort(pred:Operation):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Quicksorts the elements in the sequence. Is supplied with an operation of the form @Operation(x,y) predicate en-d where x and y will be elements in the sequence. An example predicate might be x &lt; y. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>ref(nameSpaces:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>ooks up a namespace path represented as a sequence of strings to the element found at the path. The operation takes a sequence of namespaces as an argument; the namespace arguments are used as the basis for the lookup.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>reverse():Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Reverses a sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>sel():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns one element from a sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>select(predicate:Element):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Applies a filter to a sequence of elements.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>separateWith(sep:String):String</entry>
                  <entry>Constructs a string by concatenating the elements of a sequence together, separated by sep.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>set(key:Element,value:Element):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Sets the value of a binding in a sequence indexed by key. Creates a binding if one does not exist.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>size():Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the size of a sequence. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>sort(pred:Element):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Sorts a sequence using a comparison predicate of the form @Operation(x,y) predicate end. The predicate must be a comparison expression, e.g. x &lt; y.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>sortByString():Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Sorts by string value.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>sortNamedElements():Seq(NamedElement)</entry>
                  <entry>Sorts a sequence of named elements. This operation is implemented in the kernel as is therefore very fast.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>sortNamedElements_CaseIndependent():Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Sorts named elements by names ignoring case.</entry>
                </row>
				<row>
				  <entry>sortNames():Seq(String)</entry>
				  <entry>Sorts a sequence of names.</entry>
				</row>
                <row>
                  <entry>subSequence(starting:Element,terminating:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Produces a subsequence given two indices. The first index is inclusive and is the starting index. The second index is exclusive and is the terminating index.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>subst(new:Element,old:Element,all:Boolean):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Substitutes old for new in a sequence. If all is true, it will replace all elements, otherwise it will replace the first element.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>tail():Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the tail of a sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>take(n:Integer):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Takes n elements from the tail of a sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>toString():String</entry>
                  <entry>Produces a printed representation of a sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>zip(s:Seq(Element)):Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Produces a sequences of pairs by matching the first element of a sequence with the first element of s, and so on...</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Examples</title>

        <para><programlisting>Seq{"red"}+Seq{"green"} = Seq{"red","green"}
Seq{"red"}-&gt;at(0) = "red"
Seq{"red","green"}-&gt;last() = "green"
Seq{"red"}-&gt;insertAt(0,"green") = Seq{"red","green"}
Seq{"red","green"}-&gt;indexOf("green") = 1
Seq{"red","green","amber"}-&gt;subSequence(1,2) = Seq{"green"}
Seq{"red","green","amber"}-&gt;tail() = Seq{"green","amber"}</programlisting>The
        operation butLast returns all elements in a sequence but the last
        element. It could have been defined as follows, note the use of
        Seq{head | tail} to construct a sequence with the given head and
        tail:<programlisting>context Seq(Element)
  @Operation butLast():Seq(Element)
    if self-&gt;size = 0
    then self.error("Seq(Element)::butLast: empty sequence.")
    else if self-&gt;size = 1
      then Seq{}
      else Seq{self-&gt;head | self-&gt;tail-&gt;butLast}
      end
    end
  end</programlisting></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sets</title>

      <para>A set is a list of values that may not have duplicates. A set
      literal is denoted by enumerating the elements in a Set{}. For example,
      a set of numbers: Set{1,2,3}. Sets can be nested, for example:
      Set{Set{“a”,”b”},1}. The default value of a set is the empty set, Set{}.
      A Set(Element) is an instance of the Set type. It contains the elements
      in the set.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Operators</title>

        <para>Two sets can be tested for equality and inequality. Two sets are
        equal provided they contain the same elements irrespective of
        order.</para>

        <para><table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Operator</entry>
                  <entry>Syntax</entry>
				  <entry>Result Type</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>equals</entry>
                  <entry>a = b</entry>
				  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>not equals</entry>
                  <entry>a &lt;&gt; b</entry>
				  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Operations</title>

        <para><table>
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>asSeq():Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Turns a set into a sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>asSet():Set(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Turns a set into a set.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>collect(filter:Element):Set(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the set of elements that result from evaluating filter over a set.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>contains(element:Element):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a set contains an element.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>default():Set(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the default value of a set: the empty set.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>dot(name:String):Set(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the result of iterating over a set and applying dot to the slot named name.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>edit():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Launches a browser for a set.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>excluding(element:Element):Set(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>The set excluding the element.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>exists(pred:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if an element satisfying the predicate exists in a set.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>flatten():Set(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Turns a set of sets into a set.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>includes(element:Element):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a set includes element.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>includesAll(c:Collection(Element)):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if a set includes all elements from another collection.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>including(element:Element):Set(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>The result of the set including element.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>intersection(set:Set(Element)):Set(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the intersection of two sets.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>isEmpty():Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if the set is empty.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>isKindOf(type:Classifier):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Returns true if all elements in a set are of the type.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>iter(iterator:Element,value:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Iterates over the elements in the set</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>max():Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Find the element with the maximum value in the set.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>power():Set(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the powerset of elements in a set, i.e. all possible subsets of a set including the empty set.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>reject(pred:Element):Set(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Rejects any elements in the set that satisfy the predicate.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>sel():Element</entry>
                  <entry>Selects a single element from a set.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>select(predicate:Element):Set(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Selects any elements in the set that satisfy the predicate.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>size():Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the size of the set.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>toString():String</entry>
                  <entry>Prints the set as a string/</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>union(set:Set(Element)):Set(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the union of the two sets.</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Examples</title>

        <para><programlisting>Set{1,2,3}-&gt;includes(1) = true
Set{1,2,3}-&gt;includesAll(1,2) = true
Set{1,2,3}-&gt;including(4) = Set{1,2,3,4}
Set{1,2,3}-&gt;excludes(1) = false
Set{1,2,3}-&gt;excludesAll(Set{4,5}) = true
Set{1,2,3}-&gt;excluding(1) = Set{2,3}
Set{1,2}-&gt;union(Set{2,3}) = Set{1,2,3}
Set{1,2,3} - Set{1,2,3} = Set{}
Set{1,2}-&gt;intersection(Set{2,3}) = Set{2}
Set{}-&gt;isEmpty() = true
Set{1,2,3}-&gt;size() = 3
Set{1}-&gt;sel() = 1
Set{Set{1},Set{2}}-&gt;flatten() = Set{1,2}</programlisting>Suppose that the
        set operation includes was not provided as part of XOCL. It could be
        defined by:<programlisting>context Set(Element)
  @Operation includes(e:Element):Boolean
    if self-&gt;isEmpty
    then false
    else
     let x = self-&gt;sel
     in if x = e
       then true
       else self-&gt;excluding(x)-&gt;includes(e)
       end
     end
   end
end</programlisting></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Symbols</title>

      <para>Symbol is a sub-class of String. Whereas there may be two
      different strings with the same sequence of characters, there can only
      be one symbol with the same sequence of characters. This is useful when
      using names as the basis for lookup (in tables). For example XMF ensures
      that classes, packages, operations, slots are named using symbols so
      that the lookup of these features by name is as efficient as possible.
      If strings were used the lookup would necessarily involve a
      character-by-character comparison. Using symbols the lookup can use the
      symbols identity as the comparison operator. You can reference a symbol
      by constructing an instance: Symbol(name).</para>

      <section>
        <title>Operations</title>

        <para><table>
            <tgroup cols="3">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Operator</entry>
                  <entry>Syntax</entry>
                  <entry>ResultType</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>equals</entry>
                  <entry>a = b</entry>
				  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>not equals</entry>
                  <entry>a &lt;&gt; b</entry>
				  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>greater</entry>
                  <entry>a &gt; b</entry>
				  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>less than</entry>
                  <entry>a &lt; b</entry>
				  <entry>Boolean</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>Symbols can be compared for equality, non-equality, greater
        than and less than, in which case the usual lexicographic ordering
        applies.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tables</title>

      <para>A table associates keys with values. Any element can be used as a
      key. A table has an initial size and can support any number of values.
      Use 'hasKey/1' to determine whether a table contains a key. Use 'get/1'
      to access a table via a key and 'put/2' to update a table given a key
      and a value. Use 'keys/0' to access the set of keys for a table.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Operations</title>

        <para><table>
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>get(key:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Return the value of the supplied key in the table. If the key does not exist then an exception is raised. Use 'hasKey/1' to check if the key exists.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>hasKey(key:Element):Boolean</entry>
                  <entry>Tests whether the table has a key or not.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>keys():Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns all the keys in the table.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>pprint():String</entry>
                  <entry>This operation prints out all the entries in a table.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>put(key:Element,value:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Add an association between the supplied key and value. Any existing association for the key is removed.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>ref(index:Integer):Element</entry>
                  <entry>No Documentation Specified</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>remove(key:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Remove the supplied key from the table. This succeeds whether the key exists in the tabel or not. Any daemons defined for the table are performed. The table is returned.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>set(index:Integer,value:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>No Documentation Specified</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>size():Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the size of a table.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>toString():String</entry>
                  <entry>Returns a string representation of a table.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>values():Set(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Returns all elements in the tables as a set.</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Examples</title>

        <para>The following example adds and retrieves elements from a
        table:<programlisting>context Root
  @Class Fill
    @Attribute table : Table(1000) end
    @Operation add(key,element)
      self.table.put(key,element)
    end
    @Operation retrieve(key)
      self.table.get(key)
     end
  end</programlisting></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Threads</title>

      <para>XOCL provides threads for concurrent processing. A new thread of
      control is created using the special form:<programlisting>@Fork(n) 
  body
end</programlisting>where n is a name used to identify the thread and body is
      an XOCL expression that is run when the thread starts. At any time the
      XVM is executing a single thread of control. The thread continues on the
      XVM until either it performs a read operation that blocks on input or
      when it explicitly calls yield. All XOCL values implement the yield
      operation. In both cases the thread is said to yield control. When a
      thread yields control, the XOS schedules another thread that is waiting.
      The scheduling algorithm aims to ensure that all waiting threads get
      scheduled providing that they yield.</para>

      <para>Note that XMF is not intended to be a heavy-weight concurrent
      programming environment. Threads are provided for light-weight use,
      primarily for handling multiple connections from processes that
      communicate with XMF via input and output channels. There is nothing to
      stop threads being used to implement a variety of concurrent process
      architectures, however there are no facilities in XMF for controlling
      concurrent access to resource (such as locks, monitors etc).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Vectors</title>

      <para>Vectors provide an efficient way of maintaining and accessing an
      array of values. Vectors are created using the constructor
      Vector(&lt;vector length&gt;), where size is the length of the vector. A
      vector is indexed starting at position 0.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Operations</title>

        <para>A vector is a fixed length array of elements. They are created
        using the constructor Vector(). Vectors provide very efficient insert
        (put/2) and lookup operations (ref/1).</para>

        <para><table>
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>asSeq():Seq(Element)</entry>
                  <entry>Converts a vector into a sequence. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>asString():String</entry>
                  <entry>Converts a vector to a string.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>copyInto(vector:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Copies the elements of vector into self starting at position 0.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>put(index:Element,value:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Put the element value into a vector at position index.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>ref(index:Element):Element</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the value at position index in a vector.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>size():Integer</entry>
                  <entry>Returns the size of a vector.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>toString():String</entry>
                  <entry>Returns a string representation of a vector.</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Examples</title>

        <para>The following operation creates a vector and populates it with
        element.<programlisting>context Vector
  @Operation fill(element:Element)
     @For e in 0.to(self.size()) do
       self.put(e,element)
     end
  end</programlisting></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Debugging</title>

      <para>XOCL operation invocation can be traced to check whether the
      operator is being called correctly. To trace an operation send it a
      trace message with no arguments. To stop the trace, send it an untrace
      message with no arguments. A traced operation will print out its
      arguments when it is called and its return value when it returns. All
      the operations defined in a name space N can be traced and untraced by
      N.traceAll() and N.untraceAll().</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Relationship to OCL and ASL</title>

    <para>XOCL is intended to be a superset of OCL, providing many additional
    operations and data types over standard OCL. There are a few places where
    XOCL differs from standard OCL however. These include the following
    features:</para>

    <para><table>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>XOCL</entry>
              <entry>Standard OCL</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>OCL tags, e.g. inv: and pre: are not supported</entry>
              <entry>These tags are defined by the grammar declaration, e.g. @OCL or by the context of the form it is being typed into.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>isKindOf</entry>
              <entry>oclIsKindOf</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>collect</entry>
              <entry>Standard OCL collect always flattens the resulting collection. In XOCL flattening is not automatic, so the flatten operation must be applied where required.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>iterate</entry>
              <entry>Does not currently support types in accumulator declaration, e.g: -&gt;iterate(a x : Integer = 0 | ...)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>XOCL currently does not support Bags</entry>
              <entry>Standard OCL supports Bags</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>ASL (the Action Semantics Language) is the OMG’s standard
    language for expressing dynamic behaviour. It is particularly oriented
    towards capturing concurrent and real-time behaviour. Although XOCL
    incorporates some of the features of ASL, XOCL is intended to fill a
    different gap: that of a general-purpose metaprogramming language. It
    therefore does not incorporate many of the complex features provided by
    ASL.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>XOCL Grammar</title>

    <para><programlisting>  AName ::= Name | Drop. 

  Apply ::= PathExp Args | KeyArgs .

  ArithExp ::= UpdateExp [ ArithOp ArithExp ].

  ArithOp ::= '+' | '-' | '*' | '/'.

  Args ::= '(' (')' | Exp (',' Exp)* ')'.

  AtExp ::= '@' AtPath @ 'end'.

  AtPath ::= Name ('::' Name)*.

  Atom ::= VarExp | 'self' | Str | Int | IfExp | Bool | LetExp | 
           CollExp | AtExp | Drop | Lift | '(' Exp ')' | Throw | Try | 
           ImportIn | Float.

  AtomicPattern ::= Varp | Constp | Objectp | Consp | Keywordp.
    
  Binding ::= AName '=' LogicalExp.

  Bindings ::= Binding (';' Binding)*.

  Bool ::= 'true' | 'false'.

  CollExp ::= SetExp | SeqExp. 

  CompareExp ::= ArithExp [ CompareOp CompareExp ].

  CompareOp ::= '='| '&lt;' | '&gt;' | '&lt;&gt;' | '&gt;=' | '&lt;='. 

  CompilationUnit ::= ParserImport* Import* (Def | TopLevelExp)* EOF.
  
  Consp ::= Pairp | Seqp | Emptyp.

  Constp ::=  Int | Str | Bool | Expp.

  Def ::= 'context' PathExp Exp. 
 
  Drop ::= '&lt;' Exp '&gt;'. 

  EmptyColl ::= Name '{' '}'.

  Emptyp ::= Name '{' '}'.

  Exp ::= OrderedExp.
    
  Expp ::= '[' Exp ']'.
    
  Float ::= Int '.' Int.

  Import ::= 'import' TopLevelExp.

  ImportIn ::= 'import' Exp 'in' Exp 'end'.

  ParserImport ::= 'parserImport' Name ('::' Name)* ';' ImportAt.

  IfExp ::= 'if'Exp 'then'Exp IfTail.

  IfTail ::= 'else' Exp 'end' | 'elseif' Exp 'then' Exp IfTail | 'end'.

  KeyArgs ::= '[' (']' | KeyArg (',' KeyArg)* ']'.
    
  KeyArg ::= Name '=' Exp.
    
  Keywordp ::= Name ('::' Name)* '[' Keyps ']'.
    
  Keyps ::= Keyp (',' Keyp)* | .
    
  Keyp ::= Name '=' Pattern.
    
  Lift ::= '[|' Exp '|]'.

  LetBody ::= 'in'Exp| 'then' Bindings LetBody.

  LetExp ::= 'let'Bindings LetBody 'end'.
    
  LogicalExp ::= NotExp [ LogicalOp LogicalExp ].

  LogicalOp ::= 'and' | 'or' | 'implies'.

  NonEmptySeq ::= Name '{' Exp ((',' Exp)* '}' | '|' Exp '}').
    
  NonEmptyColl ::= Name '{' Exp (',' Exp)* '}'.

  NotExp ::= CompareExp | 'not' CompareExp.

  Objectp ::= Name ('::' Name)* '(' Patterns ')'.

  OrderedExp ::= LogicalExp [ ';' OrderedExp ].

  OptionallyArgs ::= Args | .

  Pairp ::= Name '{' Pattern '|' Pattern '}'.
    
  PathExp ::= Atom [ '::' AName ('::' AName)* ].

  Pattern ::= AtomicPattern ('-&gt;' Name '(' Pattern ')')* ('when'  Exp  | ).

  Patterns ::= Pattern (',' Pattern)* | .
    
  RefExp ::= Apply 
      (
        '-&gt;' 
         (
            'iterate' '(' AName AName '=' Exp '|' Exp ')' 
          | 
           AName 
            ( 
              OptionallyArgs 
            | 
              '(' AName '|' Exp ')'  
            |
            
            ) 
          ) 
     
        | 
          '.' AName 
          (
            Args
          |   
          
          )   
      )*. 
  
    Seqp ::=  Name '{' Pattern SeqpTail.

    SeqpTail ::= ',' Pattern SeqpTail | '}'.
    
    SeqExp ::= EmptyColl | NonEmptySeq.

    SetExp ::= EmptyColl | NonEmptyColl. 

    Throw ::= 'throw' LogicalExp.

    TopLevelExp ::= LogicalExp ';'.

    Try ::= 'try' Exp 'catch' '(' Name ')' Exp 'end'.

    UpdateExp ::= RefExp (':=' ! LogicalExp | ).

    VarExp ::= Name Token.

    Varp ::= AName ('=' Pattern | ) (':' Exp | ).</programlisting></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Pattern Grammar</title>

    <para><programlisting>Pattern ::= Add ('-&gt;including(' Pattern ')')* [ 'when' Exp ].

Add ::= Atom [ '+' Add ].

Atom ::= Varp | Constp | Cnstrp | Seqp | Setp | Syntaxp | '(' Pattern ')'.

Varp ::= Name [ '=' Pattern ] [ ':' Type ]

Constp ::= Integer | String | Boolean | '[' Exp ']'

Cnstrp ::= BOAp | Keyp

BOAp ::= Path '(' [ Pattern (',' Pattern)* ] ')'

Keyp ::= Path '[' [ Name '=' Pattern (',' Name '=' Pattern ] ']' 

Seqp ::= 'Seq{' [ Pattern (',' Pattern)* ] '}' | 'Seq{' Pattern '|' Pattern '}'

Setp ::= 'Set{}'

Syntaxp ::= '[|' Exp '|]'.

Path ::= Name ('::' Name)*.</programlisting></para>
  </section>
</chapter>