<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"-->
<chapter>
  <title>Constructing a Textual Syntax and Parser</title>

  <para>This chapter demonstrates how a textual syntax can be constructed in
  XBNF: a language for defining grammars and mappings of grammars to
  models.</para>

  <para>Here we show how this can enable us to parse code and synthesise
  instances of models. However, XBNF supports many other powerful
  capabilities, including capabilities for extending the grammars of existing
  languages and for conveniently synthesising code.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Parsing and Synthesising Instances of Models</title>

    <para>We want to synthesise instances of the following model by parsing in
    a textual representation:</para>

    <programlisting>parserImport XOCL;

context Root

  @Package EntityModels
  
    @Doc
      A Simple Entity Model
    end
    
    @Class Named extends XOCL::Syntax
      @Attribute name : String end
    end
    
    @Class EntityModel extends Named
      @Attribute entities : Set(Entity) end
    end
    
    @Class Entity extends Named
      @Attribute relationships : Set(Relationship) end
    end
    
    @Class Relationship extends Named
      @Attribute type : String end
    end
    
  end</programlisting>

    <para>Note that the class <emphasis role="bold">Named</emphasis> extends the class <emphasis role="bold">XOCL::Syntax</emphasis>. It is
    necessary for all classes we want to synthesise to inherit from this
    class.</para>

    <para>The code for a grammar for this language is shown below:</para>

    <programlisting>parserImport XOCL;
parserImport Parser::BNF;

import EntityModels;

context EntityModel

  @Grammar extends OCL::OCL.grammar
  
    EntityModel ::=
      name = Name 
      entities = Entity* 'end'
        {EntityModel[name = name, entities = entities]}.
      
    Entity ::= 'entity' name = Name rels = Relationship*
      {Entity[name = name, relationships = rels]}.
      
    Relationship ::= 'rel' name = Name '-&gt;' type = Name
      {Relationship[name = name, type = type]}.
    
  end</programlisting>

    <para>Note, just as with the XML grammar in the previous chapter, we
    define a series of grammar rules that synthesise instances of the
    model.</para>

    <para>Here are some points to note:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The grammar first imports the parsers for XOCL and BNF. It also
        imports the EntityModels package (which must be loaded). The grammar
        of the EntityModel class is defined as follows:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The root of the grammar is the rule EntityModel.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A rule is sequences of pattern declarations followed by an
            action (in curly brackets) which is called after the parsing has
            occurred.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the case of the EntityModel rule, it is defined to be a
            name, followed by a sequence of Entity (which is bound to the
            variable entities).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The result of parsing an EntityModel is to create an
            instance of a EntityModel class with the variables name and
            entities populated with the above values.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>An Entity is the string ‘name’ and a sequence of
            Relationships (bound to the variable rels). The result of parsing
            it is to create an instance of a Event class with the variable
            name passed as a parameter.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A similar rule is used for Relationships.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The following is a small example of a model written in the
    syntax:</para>

    <programlisting>parserImport EntityModels;

import EntityModels;

Root::p :=
  @EntityModel Customers 
    entity Customer
      rel Owns -&gt; Account
    entity Account
  end;</programlisting>

    <para>Compiling and loading the above three files in order will load the
    model, the parser definition and the example. The result will be stored in
    the Root variable <emphasis role="bold">p</emphasis>, which can be edited in the console using
    <emphasis role="bold">p.edit()</emphasis>.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>