<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"-->
<chapter id="programming">
  <title>Using the Programming Interface</title>

  <para>This section shows how to use the programming interface to construct
  some of the models described above. We will add use the programming
  interface (see Part 1 of this guide) to construct the code.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Getting Started</title>

    <para>Select File Browser .. from the File menu. Choose a directory (or
    create one), where you want the code to reside.</para>

    <para>Right click on the directory and choose New XMF File From Template
    &gt; Package to create an XMF file.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/createafile.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The file will contain the default declarations needed to construct
    an XMF package definition. Change the name of the file to
    Components.xmf.</para>

    <para>We will be creating a package in the context of the Root package, so
    make sure that the context is set to Root. There are no imports.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/newfile.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Code can now be entered for each of the classes in the model. For a
    detailed guide to XOCL and XMF classes and package see Part 3 of this
    guide.</para>

    <para>The following code constructs the classes used in the Airports
    model. Note that constructors have been added for each class, and that
    attributes have getters (?) and setters (!), and in the case of Set and
    Sequence types, updators (+) and removers (-).</para>

    <programlisting>parserImport XOCL;

context Root
  @Package Components
  
    @Doc The Components model end
  
    @Class ComponentModel 

      @Attribute components : Set(Component) (?,!,+,-) end
      @Attribute connectors : Set(Connector) (?,!,+,-) end

      @Constructor(components,connectors) end
    
    end
     
    @Class Component extends NamedElement

      @Attribute owner : ComponentModel (?,!,+,-) end
      @Attribute ports : Set(Port) (?,!,+,-) end

      @Constructor(ports,owner,name) end
      
    end
     
    @Class NamedElement isabstract 

      @Attribute name : String (?,!) end

      @Constructor(name) ! end

    end
      
    @Class Connector 

      @Attribute target : Port (?,!) end
      @Attribute source : Port (?,!) end

      @Constructor(target,source) ! end

    end
    
    @Class Port extends NamedElement

      @Attribute type : String (?,!) end

      @Constructor(type,name) ! end

    end
  end</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Compiling and Loading</title>

    <para>At any point, right click on the editor and select Save, Compile and
    Load to save, compile and load the model.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Checking the Model</title>

    <para>The contents of the model can be checked in the property editor by
    editing the package via the console.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/editingthepackage.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>To view the package in the browser, enter the package name,
    Airports, followed by .browse().</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Adding Constraints</title>

    <para>Constraints can be added by using the @Constraint end
    declaration.</para>

    <para>As an example, let’s add a constraint that checks for source and
    target port types:</para>

    <programlisting>   @Class Connector 

      @Attribute target : Port (?,!) end
      @Attribute source : Port (?,!) end

      @Constructor(target,source) ! end

      @Constraint ValidPortTypes
        source.type = target.type
      end

    end</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Adding Operations</title>

    <para>Operations can be added in exactly the same way: This operation
    returns all the connectors whose port types don't match</para>

    <programlisting>   @Class ComponentModel 

      @Attribute components : Set(Component) (?,!,+,-) end
      @Attribute connectors : Set(Connector) (?,!,+,-) end

      @Constructor(components,connectors) end

      @Operation dontMatch()
        connectors-&gt;select(c |
          c.source.type &lt;&gt; c.target.type)
      end
    end</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Context</title>

    <para>A context is a powerful device for adding new elements to a class or
    package. It enables different aspects of an element to be separated out
    and declared elsewhere.</para>

    <para>To use a context, first declare the context, and then the element
    that is to be added to it. For example, we can add the ValidPortTypes
    constraint using a context.</para>

    <programlisting>context Connector      
      @Constraint ValidPortTypes
        source.type = target.type
      end
</programlisting>

    <para>Note, this must be declared outside of the Airports package
    declaration to be syntactically valid.</para>

    <para>In general, any element that has an owner can make use of context,
    including attributes, operations, classes and packages.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Importing Packages</title>

    <para>Import declarations enable the contents of other packages to be
    imported so that they can be referenced by other elements. For instance,
    let’s say we wanted to separate out the constraints of the Components
    model from the class. We can create a new file called ComponentsCons.xmf
    that contains the constraints:</para>

    <para>Provided that we have loaded the Components package, we can compile
    and run the new file and the constraints will be added to the appropriate
    classes.</para>

    <programlisting>parserImport XOCL;

import Components;

context Connector

  @Constraint ValidPortTypes
        source.type = target.type
      end</programlisting>

    <para>Imports are transitive, and can be used to any depth.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>