<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"-->
<chapter>
  <title>Namespace, Classes, Packages and MetaClasses</title>

  <para></para>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>NameSpaces</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Classes</title>

    <para>XMF is a class-based object-oriented modelling environment. Each
    value in XMF has a type or classifier that describes its structure and
    behaviour. Values in XMF are divided into objects and non-objects. Object
    types are called classes and non-object types are called classifiers. If a
    value v is of a type c then we say that v is an instance of c. XMF is
    provided with a large number of classes and classifiers; XMF developers
    can define their own classes and classifiers as extensions of those
    provided.</para>

    <para>Classes and classifiers classify their instances by running
    constraints. A constraint is a boolean valued expression that runs in the
    context of the current state of the candidate instance. The outcome of
    constraint checking is a constraint report containing details of the
    constraints that were performed, the candidates, the outcome and a reason
    for any constraints that failed. Constraint checking is a powerful
    mechanism for checking whether a model or a model scenario is correctly
    formed.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Class Definition</title>

      <para>A class describes the structure and behaviour of its instances. A
      class has a name and lives in a name-space. The following is a basic
      class that lives in the name-space Root:</para>

      <para><programlisting>context Root

  @Class EmptyClass

  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>By default, the class EmptyClass specializes the XMF class
      XCore::Object and provides a single constructor for creating instances:
      EmptyClass(). If we perform the following expression:</para>

      <para><programlisting>EmptyClass().isKindOf(EmptyClass)</programlisting></para>

      <para>then the result is true since the newly created instance is
      directly an instance of EmptyClasss. In addition, the expression:</para>

      <para><programlisting>EmptyClass().isKindOf(Object) and EmptyClass().isKindOf(Element)</programlisting></para>

      <para>returns true since EmptyClass inherits (by default) from Object
      and Object inherits from Element (the class Element does not inherit
      from anywhere). The class EmptyClass is itself a value:</para>

      <para><programlisting>EmptyClass.isKindOf(Class) and 
EmptyClass.isKindOf(Classifier) and 
EmptyClass.isKindOf(NamedElement) and
EmptyClass.isKindOf(Object) and 
EmptyClass.isKindOf(Element)</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title> Attributes</title>

      <para>A class typically defines some attributes that correspond to slots
      in the instances of the class. Each attribute has a name and a type and
      may optionally have some modifiers and an initial value. The following
      is a simple example of a class with attributes:</para>

      <para><programlisting>context Root
  @Class Point 
    @Attribute x : Integer end
    @Attribute y : Integer end
    @Constructor(x,y) ! end
  end
</programlisting>A new point is creates using the constructor defined by
      Point. A class may define any number of constructors; each constructor
      must have a different number of arguments. Each constructor argument
      corresponds to one of the attributes in the class. The optional modifier
      ! declares that the printed representation for a point is defined by
      that constructor.</para>

      <para>A new Point is constructed:<programlisting>Point(100,200)</programlisting>where
      100 is the value of the slot x and 200 is the value of the slot y.
      Accessor and updater operations are automatically produced by including
      attribute modifiers:</para>

      <programlisting>context Root
  @Class Point 
    @Attribute x : Integer (?,!) end
    @Attribute y : Integer (?,!) end
    @Constructor(x,y) ! end
  end</programlisting>

      <para>The modifier ? defines that operations getX and getY are
      automatically provided; modifier ! defines that operations setX and setY
      are automatically provided:</para>

      <programlisting>let p = Point(100,200)
in p.setX(p.getX() - 1);
   p.setY(p.getY() - 1)
end</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Operations</title>

      <para>Object-oriented execution proceeds by message passing; a message
      consists of a name and some argument values. When a message is sent to
      an object, the name is looked up in the class of the object (and its
      parents); if an operation is found then it is invoked otherwise an error
      is reported. Operations may be defined as part of a class or a package
      definition or added to existing classes and packages via a context
      defintion.</para>

      <para>The following defines a class of stacks and adds the definition to
      a package named Stacks. The example shows the complete contents of a
      file containing the definition. XMF can be used in a file-based mode
      where files contain source code that is compiled using the XMF compiler.
      The compiled binary is then loaded into XMF.</para>

      <programlisting>parserImport XOCL;

context Stacks

  @Class Stack
  
    @Attribute elements : Seq(Element) end
    @Attribute index : Integer end 
    
    @Operation isEmpty():Boolean
      self.elements-&gt;isEmpty
    end
    
    @Operation pop()
      if self.isEmpty()
      then throw StackUnderflow(self)
      else 
        let head = elements-&gt;head
        in self.elements := elements-&gt;tail;
           head
        end
      end
    end

    @Operation push(e:Element)
      self.elements := Seq{e | elements}
    end

    @Operation top()
      if self.isEmpty()
      then throw StackUnderflow(self)
      else elements-&gt;head
      end
    end
</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Constraints</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Inheritance</title>

      <para>All classes are specializations or sub-classes of at least one
      other class. By default a class is a sub-class of XCore::Object. A class
      inherits constructors, attributes, operations and constraints from its
      parent. For example the following class specializes Point with a z
      co-ordinate:</para>

      <para><programlisting>context Root
  @Class Point3D extends Point
    @Attribute z : Integer (?,!) end
    @Constructor(x,y,z) ! end
  end
</programlisting>An instance of Point3D may be constructed using a two-place
      constructor or a three-place constructor (the three-place is probably
      more useful). An instance of the class Point3D is also an instance of
      the parent class Point:</para>

      <para><programlisting>let p = Point3D(1,2,3)
in p.isKindOf(Point)
end</programlisting>returns true.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Multiple</title>

        <para>A class may inherit from more than one super-class in which case
        the sequence of parents is given by comma separated paths after the
        extends keyword. The order of the parents is used to determine the
        lookup order for operations, although it is considered bad practice to
        rely on the ordering when handling messages. </para>

        <para>Multiple inheritance is most useful when inheriting orthogonal
        behaviour and structure that is then extended in the new
        sub-class.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Run-Super</title>

        <para>When a sub-class extends a super-class it may shadow an existing
        operation by defining a new operation in the sub-class with the same
        name and arity as an inherited class. Sending a message to an instance
        of the sub-class will cause the shadowing operation definition to be
        performed.</para>

        <para>Sometimes it is useful to be able to reference a shadowed
        operation from a shadowing operation body. This occurs when the
        shadowing class extends the behaviour of the shadowed class. XMF
        provides the keyword super that is used to invoke the shadowed
        operation from the shadowing operation.</para>

        <para>This section provides a simple example of how super is
        used.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Packages</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Metaclasses</title>

    <para>XMF is an environment for language design and deployment. Languages
    control the structure and behaviour of the values that they denote. In
    this sense, language design is a meta-activity and requires a
    meta-language that represents the structure and behaviour of the language
    components.</para>

    <para>XMF provides a meta-circular object-oriented kernel language called
    XOCL. The meta-circular property means that XOCL is defined completely in
    itself. This property validates XOCL as a meta-language.
    Object-orientation provides a basis for application extension and reuse
    through inheritance and modularity through encapsulation. </para>

    <para>XOCL is both meta-circular and object-oriented, it is suitable for
    language definition where languages can be easily constructed as modular
    extensions of the basic XOCL language. Instantiations of XOCL are
    languages and extensions of XOCL are meta-languages.</para>

    <para>All languages have key semantic features that can be represented as
    an interface in the definition of the language. Consider a language with
    an operational semantics. In this case programs written in the language
    may be viewed as controlling a machine that contains the state of the
    execution at any given snapshot in time. The key semantic features of the
    language form the API of the machine.</para>

    <para>Given a language L, we would like to construct a new language that
    is L-like. If L is defined using object-oriented principles then it is
    attractive to construct the new language as an extension of L using
    inheritance. Syntax structures and values of the new language can be
    defined by extending the appropriate features of L. We would like to
    construct the semantics of the new language using the same approach. If we
    have constructed the semantics of L by encapsulating the key features as
    an implementation of the API as described above, then the new language
    semantics can be defined by inheriting and extending these operations as
    appropriate.</para>

    <para>Where the semantics of a language has been constructed using
    object-oriented principles, the resulting collection of classes and
    operations is referred to as a meta-object-protocol. This section
    describes the XOCL MOP. </para>

    <section>
      <title>Message Passing</title>

      <para>XOCL performs computation in terms of messages between elements. A
      message consists of a name andsome data. A message is sent from a source
      element to a target element. The target element receives themessage,
      performs appropriate computation and returns a result. Messages between
      elements aresynchronous: the source element halts computation and waits
      the return value from the target element.</para>

      <para>Message passing occurs when the source element performs an
      expression of the form: o.m(x,y,z,...) where o is the target element, m
      is the message name and x, y, z etc. is the data, or parameters, of the
      message.</para>

      <para>Message passing is defined by the MOP component referred to as the
      massage passing protocol.The protocol is defined by the meta-class of
      the target element and is called sendInstance:</para>

      <programlisting>context Element
  @Operation send(message,args):Element
    self.of().sendInstance(self,message,args)
  end
</programlisting>

      <para>A default protocol is provided by the Kernel meta-class
      Classifier:</para>

      <para><programlisting>context Classifier
  @Operation sendInstance(element,name,args)
    // Get all the operations of element with the 
    // correct name and arity. Select the most 
    // specific and invoke it.
    let arity = args-&gt;size then
        operations = element.of().allOperations()
          -&gt;asSeq
          -&gt;select(o | o.name = name and o.arity() = arity)
    in if operations-&gt;isEmpty
       then 
         element.error("Cannot handle "+message+"/"+arity)
       else operations-&gt;head.invoke(element,args)
       end
    end
  end
</programlisting>Since Class is a sub-class of Classifier, any sub-class of
      Class that defines a new sendInstance operation will provide a
      specialized message passing protocol for the instances of its instances.
      This can be used to implement specialized operation lookup mechanisms,
      to facilitiate debugging information and to change the basic message
      passing mechanisms (for example by defining a class of objects with
      message queues). </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Object Creation</title>

      <para>Objects are created by sending a new message to a class together
      with some initialization data. The preferred way of invoking the new
      operation of a class is to apply the class as an operator to the
      initialization arguments. This is preferred because it is succinct and
      because the compiler and XMF VM can handle class instantiation more
      efficiently in this form:</para>

      <para><programlisting>context Classifier
  @Operation invoke(target:Element,args:Seq(Element)):Element
    self.new(args)
  end</programlisting>The new operation is defined by the meta-class of the
      receiving class. It constitutes the instantiation procotol for a
      collection of classes. The class Classifier defines the default
      instantiation protocol:<programlisting>context Classifier
  @Operation new(args:Seq(Element)):Element
    self.new().init(args)
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>where the operation new creates an empty new instance of the
      receiver and init initializes the new instance. </para>

      <para>Sub-classes of Classifier can define their own instantiation
      protocol. Typically this will use super to create an instance using the
      default protocol and then perform some extra computation to initialize
      the new instance; however, in principle the instantiation protocol can
      by-pass the default protocol altogether. To create a raw instance of a
      class C and add a single slot named "x" with initial value 10 you can do
      the following:</para>

      <para><programlisting>let o = Kernel_mkObj()
in Kernel_setOf(o,C);
   Kernel_addAtt(o,Symbol("x",100));
   o
end</programlisting>Using the kernel-level operations, you can create a
      completely bespoke instantiation protocol. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Slot Access</title>

      <para>Objects have internal storage in the form of named slots. Access
      to a slot value is via the object and the name of the slot. Slots are
      named using symbols. Access is defined by the object's slot access
      protocol. The slot access protocol is used when an expression of the
      form o.a is performed. Access involves checking that the slot exists and
      then accessing the value of the slot.</para>

      <para>The existence of a slot can be checked using the hasSlot operation
      defined by Object:</para>

      <para><programlisting>context Object 
  @Operation hasSlot(name):Boolean
    self.of().hasInstanceSlot(self,name)
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>The hasSlot operation invokes the hasInstanceSlot operation of the
      object's class. hasInstanceSlot forms part of the slot access protocol
      for the object; the operation is defined by the object's meta-class. The
      default definition is provided by Class and uses the kernel operation
      Kernel_hasSlot to directly check whether there is a machine-level
      slot:<programlisting>context Class
  @Operation hasInstanceSlot(object,name)
    Kernel_hasSlot(object,name)
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>Access to a slot's value is provided by the operation get defined
      by Object:<programlisting>context Object
  @Operation get(name:String):Element
    self.of().getInstanceSlot(self,name)
  end
</programlisting></para>

      <para>The operation getInstanceSlot is defined by an object's meta-class
      and describes how to access the storage associated with an object and a
      slot name. The default protocol is provided by Class and uses the kernel
      operation Kernel_getSlotValue to access the machine-level slot (as added
      using Kernel_addAtt):<programlisting>context Class
  @Operation getInstanceSlot(object,name)
    Kernel_getSlotValue(object,name)
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>Typically a new slot access protocol is required because a
      collection of classes implement object storage in a non-standard way
      (for example using a table, in a data base or distributed over a
      network).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Slot Update</title>

      <para>The value of an object's slot can be updated using the object's
      slot update protocol. A slot is updated when an expression of the form
      o.a := e is performed. The class Object provides an operation used to
      set the value of a slot:<programlisting>context Object
  @Operation set(name:String,value:Element):Element
    self.of().setInstanceSlot(self,name,value);
    self
  end
</programlisting></para>

      <para>The object's meta-class defines an operation setInstanceSlot that
      forms the update protocol. The default update protocol is defined by
      Class and uses the kernel-level operation Kernel_setSlotValue to update
      the machine-level slot and to invoke any daemons that are defined on the
      object:</para>

      <para><programlisting>context Class
  @Operation setInstanceSlot(object,name,value)
    Kernel_setSlotValue(object,name,value)
  end</programlisting>A new slot update protocol is used to circumvent the
      default storage. For example the storage for a slot may be in a database
      or accessed over a network. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Default Parents</title>

      <para>A class is created as an instance of a meta-class. When a class is
      created it must have some parents. The meta-class defines an operation
      defaultParents that produces a set of classes that are the default
      parents for its instances. The basic definition for defaultParents is
      provided by Classifier:</para>

      <para><programlisting>context Classifier
  @Operation defaultParents():Set(Classifier)
    Set{Element}
  end</programlisting>Most classes are instances of the class Class, that
      overrides the definition as follows:<programlisting>context Class
  @Operation defaultParents():Set(Classifier)
    Set{Object}
  end</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Example</title>

      <para>Suppose that we want to define a class of objects that can have
      standard attribute defined slots in addition to dynamic slots. Attribute
      defined slots are defined at the class level. Dynamic slots are defined
      at the object level and can be added and removed dynamically. Both types
      of slot can be accessed and updated via the standard protocols using o.a
      and o.a := e expressions.</para>

      <para>In order to implement these objects we require a new slot access
      and update protocol. The protocol is defined at the meta-level and is to
      be called the Elastic protocol. We require two new classes:
      ElasticObject that is the super-class of all user-defined elastic
      classes; and, ElasticClass that defines the elastic protocol.</para>

      <para>The class ElasticObject uses a table to contain the dynamic
      slots:<programlisting>context Root
  @Class ElasticObject
    @Attribute slots : Table = Table(100) end
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>An elastic object provides operations to add and remove the
      dynamic slots:<programlisting>context ElasticObject
  @Operation addSlot(name:String,value)
    slots.put(Symbol(name),value)
  end

context ElasticObject
  @Operation removeSlot(name)
    slots.remove(Symbol(name))
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>An elastic object can remove all the dynamic
      slots:<programlisting>context ElasticObject
  @Operation removeAll()
    @For key inTableKeys slots do
      self.removeSlot(key.toString())
    end
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>An elastic object can increment the values of all the dynamic
      slots. Note that incAll uses the slot access and update protocol for the
      object to change the value of the dynamic slots:<programlisting>context ElasticObject
  @Operation incAll()
    @For key inTableKeys slots do
      self.set(key,self.get(key) + 1)
    end
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>The class ElasticClass defines the elastic MOP:<programlisting>context Root
  @Class ElasticClass extends Class
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>ElasticObject must be a parent of any elastic
      class:<programlisting>context ElasticClass
  @Operation defaultParents()
    Set{ElasticObject}
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>The elastic slot access protocol inspects the slots table to see
      if the required slot is defined there. If not then the protocol uses
      super to revert to the default protocol inherited from
      Class:<programlisting>context ElasticClass
  @Operation getInstanceSlot(object,name)
    if Kernel_getSlotValue(object,Symbol("slots")).hasKey(name)
    then Kernel_getSlotValue(object,Symbol("slots")).get(name)
    else super(object,name)
    end
  end

context ElasticClass
  @Operation setInstanceSlot(object,name,value)
    if Kernel_getSlotValue(object,Symbol("slots")).hasKey(name)
    then Kernel_getSlotValue(object,Symbol("slots")).put(name,value)
    else super(object,name,value)
    end
  end

context ElasticClass
  @Operation hasInstanceSlot(object,name)
    if Kernel_getSlotValue(object,Symbol("slots")).hasKey(name)
    then true
    else super(object,name)
    end
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>There is no specific need for sendInstance in the elastic
      protocol, however it is defined for completeness and simply prints a
      message before reverting to the default protocol:<programlisting>context ElasticClass
  @Operation sendInstance(element,message,args)
    format(stdout,"Sending message ~S(~{,~;~S~})~%",Seq{message,args});
    super(element,message,args)
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>There is no specific need for new in the elastic protocol, however
      it is defined for completeness and simply prints a message before
      reverting to the default protocol:<programlisting>context ElasticClass
  @Operation new(args)
    format(stdout,"Creating a new instance of an elastic class~%");
    super(args)
  end</programlisting></para>

      <para>The following is an example class definition that specifies its
      meta-class as ElasticClass:<programlisting>context Root
  @Class C metaclass ElasticClass
    @Attribute s : Element end
    @Operation test()
      self.addSlot("x",100);
      self.addSlot("y",200);
      self.addSlot("z",300);
      self.x := self.x + 1;
      self.y := self.y + 1;
      self.z := self.z + 1;
      self.incAll();
      self.s := self.x + self.y + self.z;
      self.removeAll();
      s
    end
  end</programlisting></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>