<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"-->
<chapter>
  <title>Using Manifests and Deploying Models</title>

  <para>In order to manage the compilation and loading of multiple files, XMF
  supports a convenient project management abstraction called a manifest. A
  manifest provides a convenient way of managing collections of files that
  have dependencies on each other.</para>

  <para>In version 1.0 of XMF, manifests must be declared in a file. The
  following file imports the Manifest facility and implements a manifest that
  compiles Airports.xmf file followed by AirportsCons.xmf:</para>

  <programlisting>parserImport Manifests;

@Manifest Airports
  p = @File Airports end
  @File AirportsCons end
end;</programlisting>

  <para>A manifest is declared using @Manifest. A manifest has a name (in this
  case Airports) and contains a list of files.</para>

  <para>Save, Compile and Load the Manifest (right click &gt; Save, Compile
  and Load). A manifest icon will appear in the file browser which contains
  some additional menu options:</para>

  <para>The two additional options are:</para>

  <para>Build Manifest: This will compile all the files in the
  manifest.</para>

  <para>Load Manifest: This will load the binary of the files.</para>

  <para>Compile, Build and Load: Compiles the Manifest, then Builds and Loads
  the files.</para>

  <para>These can be used to compile and load as many files as required in a
  specific development project.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Manifest Actions</title>

    <para>Actions can be added to a manifest to perform specific tasks once
    the manifest has compiled and loaded its list of files. For example, we
    might want to edit the results, or we might want to post process the
    loaded model in some way.</para>

    <para>In the following example, p is the package that results after
    loading two files: Network and NetworkCons. The action that is called
    after the “do” launches an editor for p.</para>

    <programlisting>parserImport Manifests;

@Manifest Networks
  p = @File Network end
  @File NetworkCons end do
  p.edit()
end;</programlisting>

    <para>Building and loading the manifest results in the appropriate
    property editor being launched.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Deploying Manifests</title>

    <para>Often, we don’t want to create manifests for a model by hand. XMF
    provides a deployment capability that enables manifests (and the files
    they manage) to be automatically generated from a model in the model
    editor.</para>

    <para>As an example, let’s imagine we want to generate a manifest and
    associated files for the Airports model:</para>

    <para>First right click on the packageand choose deploy.</para>

    <para>This will offer a number of deployment types.</para>

    <para>Select XOCL.</para>

    <para>Now choose the directory that you want to save the deployed code
    to.</para>

    <para>Now create a file browser (right click on any Project in the
    browser) for the created directory.</para>

    <para>Each of the classes in the model will have been deployed in code,
    along with a Manifest file.</para>

    <para>The manifest file will contain all the relevant files:</para>

    <programlisting>parserImport XOCL;
parserImport Manifests;

// Manifest deployed by Andy on Sat Sep 24 17:22:04 BST 2005

@Manifest Components
  p = @File Components end
  @File Component end
  @File ComponentModel end
  @File Port end
  @File NamedElement end
  @File Connector end
do p
end;
</programlisting>

    <para>Right click Compile, Build and Load to compile, buld and load the
    manifest.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>