<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"-->
<chapter>
  <title>Creating a Meta-Profile</title>

  <para>One common use of modelling tools is to tailor them to support a
  specific modelling domain. This typically involves specialising modelling
  concepts already provided by the tool using stereotypes and tagged values.
  The advantage of doing this is that the tool’s existing editing and drawing
  capabilities, etc, do not need to be physically changed. By combining a
  number of different stereotypes together, a “profile” can be constructed for
  a specific modelling requirement.</para>

  <para>The disadvantage of traditional stereotype and tagged value mechanisms
  is that they are essentially just a way of annotating existing model
  elements – little in the way of semantic or well-formedness information can
  be added to them.</para>

  <para>XMF supports stereotypes and tagged values, but in a way that is
  significantly more controllable and powerful than traditional tools. XMF
  enables “meta profiles” to be constructed, in which stereotyped elements are
  true instances of specialised language concepts.</para>

  <section>
    <title>An Example Profile</title>

    <para>Let’s design a data modelling profile, which allows us to construct
    a data model as an instance of a datamodel metamodel. The data modelling
    profile provides three key modelling concepts: a data model, a data entity
    and a key attribute.</para>

    <para>First, create a DBProfile project.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/creatingtheprofile.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Next, browse and show the diagram for the project.</para>

    <para>A key part of the profile is that it extends the XCore metamodel.
    This enables it to inherit the modelling capabilities of XCore - the
    language used to describe class models.</para>

    <para>Right click on the DBProfile package and select Set Parents, and
    tick the package XCore from the list.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/inheritingfromxcore.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>At this point we can open the DBProfile package and begin
    constructing the profile. We want to be able to extend existing modelling
    elements so that we can reuse their editing capabilities. Here is the
    model for the DBProfile:</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/profile.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Here a DataModel specialises the class Package, so we can now model
    with DataModels rather than Packages. A Key is a specialisation of an
    Attribute, and an Entity specialises a Class. Finally, an additional
    attribute is added to Entity to denote that some Entities are also
    containers.</para>

    <para>Note that in order to specialise the XCore classes, we simply right
    clicked on each class and selected Inheritance &gt; Add Parent.</para>

    <para>We can now create a model that makes use of this profile.</para>

    <para>First create a new project and browse the package.</para>

    <para>Rather than editing this package as an XCore package, we want to
    edit it as an instance of the profile.</para>

    <para>To do this, right click on the model package and select Set
    MetaPackage.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/settingthemetapackage.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>A list of meta packages will be displayed.</para>

    <para>Choose DBProfile.</para>

    <para>Now, open the diagram for the model package using right click
    ShowDiagram.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/newmodel.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Notice that in addition to the usual tool buttons, a new collection
    of buttons is displayed at the bottom.</para>

    <para>We can select these elements and start creating models using the new
    model elements that are provide the by profile.</para>

    <para>For instance, a new DataModel can be created, called
    Accounts.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/accountsdatamodel.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The contents of the Accounts can be viewed by showing its diagram
    (right click Show Diagram). However, when this is done, the profile
    buttons are no longer there. This is because we need to set the
    metaPackage of the model to be the profile package.</para>

    <para>We could do this by hand, but manually setting its metaPackage is
    time consuming. A more general solution is to extend the initialisation
    operation of the DataModel class so that this is done automatically. This
    is done as follows:</para>

    <para>Right click on the class and add an init() operation.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/setmetapackageoperation.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The init() operation requires a single parameter args. Because it
    extends the init() operation on the class Package, the operation calls its
    super class’s operation’s body and then sets the metaPackage.</para>

    <para>Now when we view the diagram for a DataModel, the appropriate
    buttons are available, and a model can be created.</para>

    <para>Let's create some entities:</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/creatingsomeentities.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>We now want to add an attribute to the customer class. However, in
    this case we want the attribute to be a Key. To select this, Other is
    chosen from the New &gt; Attribute menu.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/selectingattributesubclass.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The attribute name is then changed to custid.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/addinganentitykey.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Similarly, we require a Key for the Account class. We'll also add
    some other non-key attributes as well:</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/modelwithattributes.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Finally, let's add a Bank entity. In this case, we want to capture
    the fact that the Bank entity is a container. If you remember, the class
    Entity extended the attribute of the class Class, with an attribute called
    'contents'. Because the Bank is an instance of the the class Entity, we
    can now set this value to be true. To do this, right click on the Bank and
    choose Show Contents &gt; Slot Values. The result is to add a new
    compartment to the class in which the Slot Value is displayed.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/modelwithbank.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The Slot Value can be set to true by clicking on the value and
    editing it.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Adding Constraints</title>

      <para>Constraints can also be added to the profile model to rule out
      specific relationships between elements. For example, let's add a
      constraint to the class Entity that ensures it can only specialise
      another Entity.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/constraint.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>The constraint rejects parents of type Object, as all elements
      will inherit from this class. It ensures that the type of the parent
      must be the same as the child.</para>

      <para>A model can be checked to see whether it conforms to its
      constraints. Here's a model that should fail:</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/invalidmodel.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>To check the constraints on the model, we need to run
      checkConstraints on the contents of the package. To do this, right click
      on the package in the browser and select Invoke Constraints &gt;
      checkConstraints() from Container.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/checkconstraints.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>The constraint fails as we would expect.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/constraintresult.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>