<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"-->
<chapter id="mappings">
  <title>Constructing and Running Mappings</title>

  <para>Mappings are an essential part of being able to transform models
  written in one language to models written in another language. This part
  describes how to construct model to model mappings in XMap: a declarative
  pattern matching mapping language. Full details of the XMap language can be
  found in part 3 of the Bluebook.</para>

  <section>
    <title>A Simple Mapping</title>

    <para>We want to create a simple mapping from one class to another
    class.</para>

    <para>The source model is a simple domain model of Airports:</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/airlines.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Create or load the Airports model.</para>

    <para>Next, create a new project Example1 containing the classes that we
    want to map between.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/mappingclasses.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Note, the Route class has been copied from the Airports model. This
    is achieved by right clicking on the class in the Airports model,
    selecting Drop in Class Diagram and then choosing the Example1
    package.</para>

    <para>Next, a mapping is added to the model. Select the Mapping from the
    icons in the diagram editor and place it on the diagram and give it a
    name.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/addingamapping.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>A mapping must have at least one domain and a single range.</para>

    <para>Select these from the icons underneath the mapping icon.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/addingdomainandrange.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The domain is the input to the mapping and the range is its output.
    Although compulsory, it is important to think of the domain and range as
    indicating a dependency between a mapping and its constituents. In
    practice, the actual values passed to the mapping need not necessarily be
    of the domain type. Similarly, the range need not be of the target
    type.</para>

    <para>The rules and actions performed by a mapping are described by
    <emphasis>clauses</emphasis>. Add a new clause to a mapping by right
    clicking on the mapping in the diagram editor or browser and choosing New
    &gt; Clause.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/addingaclause.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Now, edit the clause by double clicking on it in the browser.</para>

    <para>A clause editor will be displayed.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="Images/aclause.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>A clause has a name, and a default clause expression followed by a
    “do” action.</para>

    <para>The expression is a pattern that must be matched before the clause
    will fire.</para>

    <para>When the clause is matched, the action after the 'do' will be
    performed.</para>

    <para>We wish to capture the rule that a Route with a capacity less than
    250 will be mapped to a ShortHaul Route with the same name. In addition,
    we want to map a Route with a capacity &gt;= 250 to a LongHaul
    Route.</para>

    <para>To achieve this we need to write two clauses. The first clause
    matches with a Route whose capacity is less than 250 and generates a Short
    Haul Route.</para>

    <para><programlisting>@Clause Short
  Airports::Route[
    name = N,
    source = S,
    destination = D,
    capacity = C]
when C &lt; 250
do
  ShortHaul[
    name = N,
    source = S,
    destination = D]
end</programlisting></para>

    <para>Here:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The name of the clause has been changed to Short</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The clause expression is a Route, whose name equals the variable
        'N', whose source and destination equals the variables 'S' and 'D' and
        whose capacity equals the variable C.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The when condition states that this clause can only fire if the
        capacity is &lt; 250.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The 'do' action creates a ShortHaul Route whose name is equal to
        the variable 'N', and which has the same source and
        destination.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Note because the variables are global they are matched across the
    clause, ensuring for example that the name of the source Route matches the
    target Route name.</para>

    <para>To enter the clause, enter the text and right click &gt; Commit
    it.</para>

    <para>To deal with the other possibility (that the capacity &gt;= 250) we
    need to create another clause and add it to the mapping.</para>

    <para>Again, right click on the mapping in the diagram editor or browser
    and choose New &gt; Clause. Edit and commit the clause as before.</para>

    <programlisting>@Clause Long
  Airports::Route[ 
    name = N, 
    source = S,
    destination = D,
    capacity = C]
when C &gt;= 250
do
  LongHaul[
    name = N,
    source = S,
    destination = D]
end</programlisting>

    <para>The code is similar to that of the previous clause, but the “when”
    condition requires that the capacity of the route is &gt;= 250. The
    resulting action creates an instance of a LongHaul Route.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Running the Mapping</title>

      <para>Mappings can be run in two ways: via the console or by passing the
      object to the mapping.</para>

      <para>Here's an example of running a mapping via the console. Let's
      create an instance of a Route, x, named "LAX2LHR", with a capacity of
      200 and source and destination "LAX" and "LHR" respectively..</para>

      <para>The mapping can be run by calling the mapping and passing it the
      Route, x.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/runningthesimplemapping.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>The result of the mapping is a ShortHaul Route whose name is
      "LAX2LHR" as we would expect.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/resultofsimplemapping.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>The same result can be achieved by creating the same instance of a
      Route in a Snapshot and selecting Apply Mapping from the object's
      menu:</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/applyingamapping.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>A choice of available mappings will be displayed. Select the
      mapping that the object is to be passed to, and it will be
      invoked.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/applychoice.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>A Simple Model to C# Mapping</title>

    <para>This section describes the construction of a mapping between model
    (XCore) packages and classes to a small model of the C# programming
    language.</para>

    <section>
      <title>The C# Model</title>

      <para>The following is a simple model of the abstract syntax of C# that
      will be used in the mapping. A C# model consists of a program containing
      a number of classes, which have attributes.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/modelofcsharp.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Mapping</title>

      <para>We'll construct two mappings. The first mapping
      (Package2CSProgram) turns a Package into a C# Program . This mapping
      then calls the Class2CSClass mapping, which iterates over the classes in
      the Package and maps them to CSClasses. Of course, further mappings can
      be constructed to map Class operations and attributes, etc, but we won't
      deal with those here.</para>

      <para>First, we need to import the Package and Class classes from the
      XCore package. To do this, open the Root::Kernel::XCore package in the
      browser. Select the classes Package and Class and then select Drop in
      Class Diagram to drop them into the mapping package. Note, we also need
      to import the C# classes CSProgram and CSClass by dropping them into the
      model from the CS model.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/importedclasses.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Next, the mappings are added. Remember that the domain and range
      arrows are added by selecting the domain and range buttons respectively.
      A dependency arrow is also added to indicate that the Package2CSProgram
      mapping is dependent on the Class2CSClass mapping.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/mapping.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Let’s add the mapping clause by starting with the simplest
      mapping. The Class2CSClass mapping transforms an instance of a Class
      into an instance of a CSClass.</para>

      <para>Its clause says that whenever the mapping is given a Class it
      returns a CSClass with the same name.</para>

      <para><programlisting>@Clause Clause0
  XCore::Class[name = N]
do
  CS::CSClass[name = N]
end</programlisting>The Package2CSProgram maps a Package to a CSProgram. In
      doing so, it maps each class in the package to a CSClass by calling the
      Class2CSClass mapping.<programlisting>@Clause Clause0
  XCore::Package[name = N, classes = C]
do
  CS::CSProgram[name = N, classes = Cs]
where
  Cs = C-&gt;collect(c | Class2CSClass()(c))
end</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Executing the Mapping</title>

      <para>Just as in the previous example, the mapping can be executed via
      the console.</para>

      <para>Because we are mapping from XCore packages, we can actually pass a
      package from a model into the mapping and see what it produces. Let's
      map the Airports package</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/runningthemapping.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>As expected, the mapping has generated a C# Program. If we edit
      it, we can see it has produced a CSClass for each class in the Airports
      package.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/mappingresult.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Mapping Hints and Tips</title>

    <section>
      <title>Error Reporting</title>

      <para>When running a mapping, all the usual exception reports will be
      displayed if for example, the mapping attempts to set an invalid slot or
      create an invalid instance. In addition, a MapFailed exception is raised
      if mapping cannot find a clause that matches the input to the
      mapping.</para>

      <para>As an example, try running the mapping by passing an invalid
      object, for instance a Class to the Package2CSProgram mapping. Because
      the Package2CSProgram mapping is expecting a Package it will fail and
      generate the following exception.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/mappingexception.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Additional information on the cause of the exception can be found
      by expanding the tree nodes.</para>

      <para>Here, the value being passed to the mapping can be seen in
      local(0).</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/expandedmappingexception.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Clearly, it is of the wrong type.</para>

      <para>If we wanted to examine the passed object in more detail it can be
      navigated to by double clicking on local(0).</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Constructing a Pretty Printer</title>

    <para>In the previous section, a mapping from packages and classes to C#
    was constructed. In practice however, the objective will be to generate
    concrete code (not just an instance of the C# model). For example, we
    might expect to generate some code of the following form:<programlisting>using System;

  class Route 
  {
    integer capacity;
    string name;
    string source;
    string destination;
  }
  class Passenger 
  {
    string name;
  }
  class Airline 
  {
    string name;
  }
  class Airport 
  {
    string name;
  }
  class Flight 
  {
    string date;
  }</programlisting></para>

    <para>The basic approach is to add operations to the language model to
    pretty print it. The first step is to load your language model and plan
    where the appropriate operations need to be added. In general, it is best
    to start at the leaf classes where there is minimum dependency on other
    elements in the model.</para>

    <para>As an example, a pretty print operation can be added to the class
    CPPAtt (a C# attribute). First, add a pretty print operation to the class
    and give it a name, e.g. pprint().</para>

    <para>Now, edit the operation. Two parameters are required by the
    operation: an output type, out, which will be used to direct the output of
    the operation to an editor or to a file, and an indent, which is the
    current indent of the code.</para>

    <para>We can now construct the body of the operation. An attribute will be
    pretty printed as the type name and the attribute name, terminated with a
    semicolon.</para>

    <para><programlisting>@Operation pprint(out : XCore::Element,indent : XCore::Element):XCore::Element
      format(out,"~V~S~%",Seq{indent, type.name + " " + name + ";"})
    end</programlisting></para>

    <para>The format command is used to generate the text. The sequence of
    control characters dictates the format of elements that occur in the
    sequence of elements that are to be formatted. For example, ~V denotes a
    vertical space, ~S is a string and ~% is a line return. Note, full details
    of the format command can be found in Part 3 of this guide.</para>

    <para>In this case an indent is inserted before the string is printed, and
    a character return is inserted after the semicolon.</para>

    <para>The definition of pprint on CSClass is as follows:</para>

    <para><programlisting>@Operation pprint(out : XCore::Element,indent : XCore::Element):XCore::Element
      format(out,"~V~S~%",Seq{indent,"class " + name + " ",indent,"{"});
      attributes-&gt;collect(a |
        a.pprint(out,indent + 2));
      format(out,"~V~S~%",Seq{indent,"}"})
    end</programlisting></para>

    <para>The class signature and name of the class is printed followed by the
    attributes and operations of the class.</para>

    <para>Finally, we need to construct the pretty printer for a
    CSProgram.</para>

    <programlisting>@Operation pprint(out : XCore::Element,indent : XCore::Element):XCore::Element
      format(out,"~V~S~%",Seq{indent,"using System;"});
      classes-&gt;collect(c |
        a.pprint(out,indent + 2))
    end
</programlisting>

    <para>If we run the pprint operation on the result of mapping the Airports
    package, the following code is generated:</para>

    <programlisting>using System;

  class Route 
  {
  }
  class Passenger 
  {
  }
  class Airline 
  {
  }
  class Airport 
  {
  }
  class Flight 
  {
  }</programlisting>

    <para>A lot more needs to be done to complete the mapping. In particular
    mappings from Attribute and Operation to C# Attributes and Operations need
    to be defined. However, it is simply a case of following the same overall
    approach.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>