<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"-->
<chapter>
  <title>XML</title>

  <para></para>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>XML is a standard data format and as such is an essential tool for
    saving XMF data and allowing XMF to interact with other tools. XMF
    provides extensive support for working with XML and in particular provides
    a declarative parser for reading sources of XML and synthesizing XMF
    data.</para>

    <para>This document describes how to work with XML in XMF. A number of
    standard formats exist for XML (such as XMI for models). This document
    does not describe these formats.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>XML</title>

    <para>XML is a markup language for character based information. An XML
    document consists of a hierarchically organised collection of elements.
    Each element has a tag, some named attributes and a body. The body of an
    element is either text or is a sequence of child elements. The following
    model shows the basic structure of XML:<mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/image004.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Parsing XML</title>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>XMF provides a number of technologies for reading sources of XML.
      In most cases, an application is required to translate the XML input
      into XMF data elements. This can be achieved by reading the XML source
      character by character, but fortunately XMF provides XML parsing
      technology that interprets declarative rules specifying how to match XML
      input and synthesize XMF elements.</para>

      <para>An XMF parser reads an XML input source and interprets an XML
      grammar. And XML grammar consists of a collection of clauses. Each
      clause defines how to match a portion of the input and how to translate
      it into XMF data. An XML grammar can be viewed as the type of an XML
      document in the same way as a DTD. Unlike DTDs, grammar components are
      associated with actions that are performed when the appropriate portion
      of the input has been successfully consumed.</para>

      <para>This section shows how to define XML grammars and how to run XML
      parsers. It starts with a number of examples that contain key technology
      features. Finally the XML grammar model is defined in full with a
      complete definition of the components.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Example</title>

      <para></para>

      <section>
        <title>Two Dimensional Tables</title>

        <para>This section gives an example of how to read the XML
        representation of a simple domain model and synthesize an instance of
        the model. The following model represents two dimensional integer
        tables:<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image006.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>Suppose that we have been supplied with an XML document that
        contains a two-dimensional integer table. We want to read the XML and
        produce an instance of the domain model. This situation occurs
        frequently in system development when we are supplied with data that
        has been exported from a third party tool and we want to process the
        information using XMF. Alternatively, it may occur when we have used
        XML as the format for storing data from a previous use of
        XMF-Mosaic.</para>

        <para>The following screen shot shows how the data could be expressed
        in XML:<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image008.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>The XML is to be parsed using a grammar that defines how to
        match tables, rows and columns. An XML grammar consists of a
        collection of clauses each of which defines how to match elements,
        their attributes and their children.</para>

        <para>An XML source (such as a file) is read and each element is
        matched against the clauses in the grammar. When a clause matches
        against the current XML input element, its action is performed causing
        an XMF element to be synthesized.</para>

        <para>Matching an element involves matching its tag, attributes and
        its children. All of these components must match in order for the
        match to be successful. Attribute values can be extracted as part of
        the matching process and passed to the synthesizing actions. Values
        synthesized by matching children can be used in the actions of a
        parent. This way information can be extracted from the XML elements as
        they are consumed and synthesized elements can be passed up the tree
        as it is consumed. Eventually the result of the parse is the value
        synthesized by the root element of the XML document. The following
        tool screenshot shows the content of a source file that defines an XML
        grammar for parsing two-dimensional tables. The file imports the
        XML::Parser package in line 1 so that the grammar for parsing XML
        grammars is available in the rest of the file. Line 4 imports the same
        package so that names can be referenced in code (for example
        ParserChannel in line 40).<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image010.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>In order to use an XML grammar to parse and synthesize an XML
        source, the grammar must be compiled. Compilation processes the
        grammar, checks it for any errors and then translates it into an
        efficient parsing table. The table is then used as the input to a
        general XML parsing engine. Compilation checks for a number of errors.
        In particular it checks that the grammar is LL(1). An LL(1) grammar
        allows the parser to proceed based on one token lookahead. In this
        case, tokens are XML elements. Fortunately, LL(1) grammars can be
        easily checked and this is done automatically for you. If you specify
        a non-LL(1) grammar, XMF will report a warning and indicate where you
        have gone wrong.</para>

        <para>To use a compiled grammar, you create an instance of
        XML::Parser::ParserChannel. The constructor for this class accepts an
        XML grammar and an XML input source. A parser channel has an operation
        parse that is used to consume input from the XML source, to run the
        parser and return the synthesized result:<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image012.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Dealing with References</title>

        <para>XML data is tree-structured. This means that data elements
        cannot be shared by multiple paths from the root element. This is not
        true of XMF data elements, and computer data structures in general.
        General data elements are graphs where individual elements may be
        shared (or pointed to) by multiple parents.</para>

        <para>This restriction on XML data representation is usually handled
        using data identifiers and references. Any element that can be
        referenced by multiple sources is allocated a unique identifier. One
        of the occurrences of the element is translated into an XML tree and
        all other occurrences are encoded in the reference source using the
        identifier. It is then up to the interpretation of the XML data to
        faithfully interpret the identifiers and their references. XMF manages
        identifiers and references automatically providing they are
        appropriately declared in the XML grammar. This section shows how this
        is achieved using a simple example of encoding graphs using
        XML.</para>

        <para>The following model is used to represent graphs:<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image014.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>A graph can be represented in XML as follows. A node can be
        accessed by the containing graph through a number of routes: via the
        nodes attribute or via the source or target attributes of edges.
        Sharing of a node through multiple routes is encoded in the XML by
        allocating a unique identifier to each node. Nodes are represented
        using an XML element with the unique tag within the graph element and
        referenced using their identifier via edges:<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image016.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>We will synthesize an instance of the graph model using an XML
        grammar. The grammar is defined as a named element in a package as
        shown below:<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image018.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>An XML element representing a node is parsed and an instance of
        the class Graph::Node is synthesized by the clause defined below. A
        node has attributes id and data which are matched and bound to clause
        variables in line 31. The clause synthesizes a node which is
        associated with the identifier bound to the variable id:<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image020.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>Edges are parsed and synthesized by the clause defined below.
        Instances of the class Graph::Edge refer to the graph nodes; but,
        nodes are not available at this point in the parse since the XML
        elements refer to the source and target nodes via their ids. An XML
        parser can indicate that an identifier reference should be replaced
        with the associated value that is synthesized elsewhere by including a
        reference in the result of the clause as shown below:<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image022.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>The following operation shows how the Graph grammar is used to
        parse a file containing a graph encoded in XML.<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image024.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Representing Models in XML</title>

        <para>Most modelling tools allow you to encode models using XML; often
        this is the only way of saving and loading models to persistent
        storage. The various versions of XMI for UML is an example of this
        kind of model encoding. XMF-Mosaic allows models to be encoded in a
        variety of ways and in particular allows you to develop your own
        encoding that suits the domain with which you are modelling. This
        section provides an overview of how models can be encoded using an
        XMI-style XML format.</para>

        <para>The following XML document shows a simple model
        encoding:<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image026.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>Models are just top-level packages containing standard elements
        such as classes and sub-packages. Each model element is allocated a
        unique identifier to facilitate cross model references. An example of
        a reference occurs in the attributes of the model where the type of
        the attribute is encoded as a reference to a class that is represented
        in full elsewhere in the document.</para>

        <para>The result of loading the XML model is shown below:<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image028.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>The model is synthesized by parsing an XML grammar. The grammar
        is shown below. Each identifier is registered against the associated
        model element during the parse using :=:<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image030.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>You should be careful when using references (instances of
        XML::Parser::Ref) as initialization arguments in class instantiation
        because class instantiation may process the arguments and expect them
        to be data values of the referenced type rather than the reference
        itself. In the following construction of a class we use a keyword
        constructor since the parents may be references (in which case
        addParent will fail since it expects a classifier rather than a
        reference).<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image032.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>The definition of Attribute below shows a typical scenario where
        XML attributes encode information that must be processed in order to
        synthesize the model element. In this case the multiplicity of the
        attribute (whether it is atomic, a set type or a sequence type) is
        encoded as an enumerated type that is processed in order to decide
        what the type of the attribute will be.<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image034.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>The following ClassRef definition shows how references are
        synthesized:<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image036.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>Finally, the following operation can be used to read a file
        containing a model that is encoded in XML:<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Images/image038.jpg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Debugging XML Grammars</title>

      <para>An XML parser channel has an attribute debug that can be used to
      provide a trace of execution. If the flag is set:<mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="Images/image040.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject></para>

      <para>then output is produced that shows the XML input as it is
      consumed, shows the result of actions as they are performed and shows
      the clause variables as they are bound. The following is a partial trace
      produced by reading a graph with debug set:<mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="Images/image042.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The XML Parsing Grammar</title>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/image044.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>DOM Input Channel</title>

    <para>The XML parser provided by XMF does not give direct access to the
    XML elements in a document. The parser matches against the XML as it is
    read and the parser actions are used to synthesize any XMF element.</para>

    <para>Certain applications require access to the XML representation of the
    data. For example, the XML model may be the domain model. In this case you
    can write an XML parser that synthesizes an instance of the XML model.
    This use case is supported directly in XMF by DOMInputChannel. The use of
    this class is equivalent to writing a bespoke parser that synthesizes XML;
    however, it is much more efficient because general parsing machinery is
    not required to recognize the XML elements as they are encountered.</para>

    <para>This section shows how DOMInputChannel works by providing a simple
    example of its use.</para>

    <para>Consider the management of some hierarchical data such as
    classification trees, component descriptions, and organisation structures.
    The data can be maintained as a database in XML format. Database queries
    and update can be implemented as operations that work directly on the XML
    data. The following Tree package defines operations that partially
    implement such a database:<mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/image046.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>The readDB operation uses a DOM input channel to read the contents
    of a standard XML file. The result of performing the parse operation is an
    XML document whose root element is the database. The constructor for the
    class DOMInputChannel accepts an input channel that produces XML
    characters when read.</para>

    <para>The following operation uses the print operation of XML::Document to
    write the database to a text file:<mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/image048.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>Once the database has been read (or constructed by directly creating
    instances of the XMLmodel). It can be manipulated using XOCL. The
    following operation adds a child to an element in the
    database:<mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/image050.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>The following query operation uses pattern matching to select an
    element:<mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/image050.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>SAX Input Channel</title>

    <para>XML input can be processed using an XML grammar or using a DOM input
    channel. The former provides a convenient way of declaring XML patterns
    and synthesizing XMF data. The latter provides a convenient way of
    translating an XML input source into an instance of the XML model.
    Occasionally, the XML instance is not required and the overhead of using
    general parsing machinery seems unnecessary. For example, if we wanted to
    count the number of elements in the input or check whether an element with
    a given tag exists in the input.</para>

    <para>For occasions where parsing is unnecessary and DOM is not required,
    XMF provides a SAX input channel. A SAX input channel processes the XML
    input by generating events each time an XML node is encountered in the
    input. The channel has handlers that are called when the events are fired.
    XMF works hard to ensure that the input is processed as efficiently as
    possible and therefore, SAX input channels are appropriate for processing
    very large XML data sources.</para>

    <para>The key operations called on an instance of SAXInputChannel are as
    follows:</para>

    <para><programlisting>startElement(tag:Buffer,attributes:Buffer)</programlisting></para>

    <para>This operation is called when each element is encountered in the
    input. The tag of the element is supplied as a string buffer and the
    attributes are supplied as a buffer containing instances of
    XML::IO::SAXAttribute with attributes name and value both of type string
    buffer. All buffers are reused in order to ensure the input is processed
    as efficiently as possible. Therefore if you wish to retain the tag, or
    the attribute names or attribute values then the buffers should be
    transformed into the equivalent strings using toString.</para>

    <para><programlisting>endElement(tag:Buffer)</programlisting></para>

    <para>This operation is called when the end tag of each element is
    encountered in the input. The tag is a string buffer that is subsequently
    reused as above.</para>

    <para><programlisting>characters(text:Buffer)</programlisting>This
    operation is called when text is encountered in the input. The text is
    supplied as a string buffer that is subsequently reused as above.</para>

    <para><programlisting>parse()</programlisting>Call this operation to start
    processing the input. No value is returned by default. Extend this
    operation in sub-classes of SAXInputChannel to construct and return values
    based on the operations defined above.</para>

    <para><programlisting>SAXInputChannel(inch:InputChanel)</programlisting>A
    constructor for SAX input channels. The argument is an input channel that
    produces XML text.</para>

    <para>This section shows how SAX input channels work in XMF by
    implementing a DOM input channel in terms of a SAX input channel. The
    following tool screenshot shows the class uses a stack to manage the XML
    nodes as they are read and synthesized by the operations defined
    above:<mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/image054.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>When the input source is parsed, the intermediate XML nodes are
    pushed and popped on the stack. Child nodes are popped when the end
    element event occurs and added to the currently open element on the stack.
    Eventually, the root node is left as the single stack element. The parse
    just pops the root node, creates and returns an XML document:<mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/image056.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>When the characters operation is called, a Text node is created and
    pushed on the stack. Note how toString is used to copy the text on the
    string buffer:<mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/image058.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>When a new element node is encountered in the input we create a new
    XML element object and push it on the stack. Between the start element
    event and the associated end element event there will be any number of
    events that create the children nodes. The children nodes will be pushed
    on the stack. When the end element event occurs it is straightforward to
    pop the child elements from the stack up to the parent element and modify
    the parent by inserting the children:<mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/image060.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>The end element event causes all the children that have been pushed
    since the corresponding parent element node to be popped and
    inserted:</para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/image062.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Images/image064.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>XML Output</title>

    <para></para>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>When developing XMF applications it is likely that you will want
      to generate XML from XMF data. This can be achieved in a number of ways
      depending on the level of control and the amount of reuse that you want
      to have over the output. This section describes approaches to XML
      output. The most direct way of producing an XML document is to print the
      characters, for example: <programlisting>format(out,”&lt;Class name=’~S’ id=’~S’/&gt;”,Seq{c.name(),c.path()}) </programlisting>This
      approach to output provides complete control over the text that is
      produced, but suffers from a lack of XML semantics – the format command
      does not know it is processing an XML element.</para>

      <para>There are two strategies for producing XML output that are more
      attractive than directly writing characters:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Generating instances of the XML model and then sending the
          instance a print message.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Using the XML::PrintXML::XML construct to specify output
          patterns.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The rest of this section describe the second of these
      approaches.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>XML Output Patterns</title>

      <para>Consider the task of translating a model to an XML document. The
      model consists of packages, classes, attributes and operations. The XML
      tags reflect the type of model elements. Models contain multiple
      references to the same model elements, this is encoded in the XML
      document using attributes whose values are unique identifiers.</para>

      <para>The following operation defines a mapping that writes a model
      element to an XML document. It uses the XML::PrintXML::XML pattern
      language:<mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="Images/image066.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject></para>

      <para>Line 12 starts a case analysis on the supplied element. The
      CaseObj construct matches the supplied value (element) against patterns
      consisting of the path to the direct classifier of the value followed by
      a number of slot names defined by the classifier. If the value is a
      direct instance of the classifier (i.e. its of operation returns the
      named classifier) then the body of the matching CaseObj clause is
      performed with the named slots bound to the corresponding slot
      values.</para>

      <para>The first pattern in line 13 matches against a package. The XML
      pattern starting in line 14 specifies some XML to be sent to the
      supplied output channel (out).</para>

      <para>Line 15 defines some XML output. The output pattern is specified
      in the same format as an XML element containing a tag and some
      attributes. The tag name and the attribute names are all literal names
      (you can also use strings or expressions in parentheses). The values of
      attributes are expressions. When a pattern is evaluated, the character
      are written to the supplied output channel; any expressions are
      evaluated and the corresponding values are transformed to
      strings.</para>

      <para>The body of the element pattern ranges over lines 16 – 21. Element
      bodies can be nested elements or program code. In 16 – 21 there is
      program code that loops through the packages and classes bound in line
      13 and calls writeXML to produce the appropriate output.</para>

      <para>The package pattern is complete at line 22 where the terminating
      tag is output.</para>

      <para>Classes are output as follows:<mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="Images/image068.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject></para>

      <para>The example above shows that XML pattern directed output can be
      nested. Line 33 uses a pattern to produce a classifier reference for the
      parents of a class; this is nested inside the pattern started in line
      30.</para>

      <para>Attributes are represented in XML as an element with a nested
      class reference for the type. The multiplicity of the attribute type is
      encoded in the attribute:<mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="Images/image070.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject></para>

      <para></para>

      <para><mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="Images/image072.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject></para>

      <para></para>

      <para><mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="Images/image074.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject></para>

      <para></para>

      <para><mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="Images/image076.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject></para>

      <para></para>

      <para><mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="Images/image078.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject></para>

      <para></para>

      <para><mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="Images/image080.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject></para>

      <para></para>

      <para><mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="Images/image082.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>XML Output Channels</title>

      <para></para>

      <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Basic XML Output</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Object Formatters</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Name Space Formatters</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Saving Models as XML</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Raising Events</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Deploying Java</title>

    <para></para>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Deploying Models</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Deploying Parsers</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Deploying Factories</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>